[ SIREN WAILING ]
USUAL WAGER?
- SURE.
THE, UH, LOSER CLEANS
THE SHOP, RIGHT?
YEAH.
- OKAY.
COUNTING IT IN,
I'M READY.
3, 2...
[ TIRES SQUEAL ]
1.
- HEY, WAIT A SECOND.
HERE WE GO.
[ CELL PHONE RINGING ]
OH.
[ BEEP ]
- HELLO?
OH, HI, MOM.
AH! NO, NO. NOT YOU.
NOT YOU.
SO, IT --
HOLD ON -- HOLD ON.
MOM, IT'S NOT REALLY
THE BEST TIME FOR ME TO TALK.
[ SHEEP BLEAT ]
[ TIRES SQUEAL ]
SATURDAY? SURE.
OH, MOM, HOLD ON.
MOM, HOLD ON.
MOM, I GOT TO GO. I GOT TO GO.
OKAY. I'LL TALK TO YOU LATER.
[ BEEP ]
[ EXPLOSION ]
AHH!
I LOST.
YOU WERE LOOKING A LITTLE
DISTRACTED THERE.
YEAH, BUT I DID PRETTY GOOD
IN REVERSE.
UH, ALL RIGHT.
- [ LAUGHS ]
--<font color="#ffff00"> Captions by VITAC</font> --
<font color="#00ffff">www.vitac.com</font>
CAPTIONS PAID FOR BY
DISCOVERY COMMUNICATIONS
ALL RIGHT, SIR.
TIME TO GET
YOUR RACING GLOVES ON.
WE HAVE AN ENTIRE EPISODE
THAT PUTS THE WORD "DANGEROUS"
INTO THE PHRASE
"DANGEROUS DRIVING."
LIKE WHAT?
WELL, WE'VE GOT A HOLLYWOOD
CAR CHASE STORY TO TACKLE,
THAT DRIVING AT
HIGH SPEED THROUGH TRAFFIC,
EVADING YOUR ENEMIES
IN REVERSE, IS EASY.
BUT FIRST UP,
WE HAVE A STORY ALL ABOUT
THE DANGERS OF DRIVING WHILE
TALKING ON YOUR CELL PHONE.
OH, THERE'S A LAW AGAINST THAT,
AT LEAST AS FAR AS
HOLDING IT IN YOUR HAND.
EXACTLY,
BUT WHAT IS THE SOLUTION
FOR SOMEONE WHO WANTS TO
TALK ON THEIR PHONE?
HANDS-FREE?
- HELLO?
YUP, BUT THERE'S A MYTH
THAT THERE IS NO IMPROVEMENT
IN SAFETY TALKING HANDS-FREE
VERSUS HOLDING ON TO YOUR PHONE,
THAT THEY BOTH DISTRACT YOU
JUST AS MUCH.
AND I THINK
WE SHOULD TEST THAT.
ABSOLUTELY.
Narrator:
TALKING ON A HANDHELD PHONE
LEAVES A DRIVER BOTH MENTALLY
AND PHYSICALLY COMPROMISED.
GOING HANDS-FREE DOES ELIMINATE
HALF THE PROBLEM.
BUT WITH THE OTHER HALF
STILL THERE,
SOME SAY THAT IT'S JUST
AS DANGEROUS.
[ TIRES SQUEAL,
GLASS SHATTERS ]
HEY! HEY! HEY!
- HEY! HEY! HEY!
Narrator: TO FIND OUT,
THE "MYTHBUSTERS" CREW
HAVE CONSTRUCTED
A CLASSIFIED COURSE
DESIGNED BY DRIVE EXPERT
DAVE STORTON.
SO THE FIRST SECTION HERE
IS A SLALOM.
SO THAT'S GONNA TEST
THEIR STEERING ABILITY
WHILE TALKING ON THE PHONE.
Narrator: RIGHT NOW
ADAM AND JAMIE ARE BEING
DELIBERATELY KEPT IN THE DARK.
Storton:
COMING OUT OF THE SLALOM,
THEY'LL IMMEDIATELY HAVE TO GET
ON THE BRAKES
FOR A LOW-SPEED EXERCISE
CALLED THE OFFSET LANE.
Narrator: BECAUSE ANY
PRE-EXISTING KNOWLEDGE OF
THE ROUTE COULD
DISCREDIT THEIR DATA.
Storton:
ONCE THROUGH THAT,
WE HEAD OVER TO
WHAT'S CALLED A T-BOX.
Narrator: INSTEAD,
ALL THEY KNOW IS THAT
THEY MUST STICK TO
THE SPEED LIMITS
AND NOT CLIP ANY CONES
IF THEY'RE TO ACHIEVE
A PERFECT SCORE.
RIGHT.
IF YOU BOLT THE TWO TOGETHER,
MAYBE SOME STICKY TAPE
IN THE MIDDLE,
AND THAT SHOULD TOTALLY --
OKAY. HOLD ON, HOLD ON, HOLD ON.
I GOT A THING TO DO.
OKAY, WAIT RIGHT THERE.
OKAY, SO WHILE WE KNOW THAT
DRIVING IN A CAR
WHILE HOLDING ON
TO A CELL PHONE AND TALKING
IS BAD --
SORRY, THAT WASN'T FOR YOU.
THE MYTH IS THAT DRIVING
HANDS-FREE IS JUST AS BAD,
THAT THERE IS NO DIFFERENCE
BETWEEN HANDS-FULL
AND HANDS-FREE.
AND WE ARE JUST ABOUT TO TEST IT
ON THE COURSE BEHIND ME.
I CAN SEE IT FROM A DISTANCE,
BUT THAT'S AS CLOSE
AS I'M GONNA GET
BECAUSE MY IGNORANCE OF THIS
COURSE IS INTRINSIC TO OUR TEST.
Narrator: LIKE ADAM,
JAMIE'S ALSO GOING
THAT EXTRA MILE TO MAKE SURE
THEIR SCIENCE IS SOUND.
ADAM'S GONNA RUN THIS TEST
TWICE,
FIRST,
WITH PHONE HELD IN HIS HAND,
AND THEN, SECONDLY, HANDS-FREE.
THEN, I'M ALSO GONNA RUN
THE TEST TWICE.
BUT I'M GONNA DO IT
IN THE INVERSE ORDER.
THE IDEA HERE IS THAT
WE'RE GONNA BE ABLE TO REMOVE
ANY BIAS AS FAR AS LEARNING,
AND GETTING BETTER EVERY TIME
WE DO THE TEST.
Narrator: INDEED.
AND WHILE ADAM WARMS UP
IN THE TEST CAR...
BREAKER, BREAKER.
WE GOT A, UH, 5-5-5 ON AN M.P.B.
I'LL TAKE CARE OF IT.
Narrator: JAMIE SITS DOWN
IN MISSION CONTROL.
ALL RIGHT,
I'VE GOT MY QUESTIONS,
I'VE GOT MY PHONE.
WE'LL SEE WHAT WE CAN DO TO MESS
WITH ADAM'S WORLD.
HELLO, SIR.
- HELLO.
Narrator: WITH DAVE RIDING
SHOTGUN TO MARK ADAM'S MOVES,
IT'S TIME TO HOLD THE PHONE.
[ CELL PHONE RINGS ]
HELLO.
- Hello, Adam.
I'VE GOT MY QUESTIONS READY
FOR YOU AND WE'RE GOOD TO GO.
3, 2, 1, HERE WE GO.
OKAY, SO, IF YOU COULD COMPETE
WITH THE OLYMPICS,
WHAT EVENT WOULD YOU
WANT TO BE IN?
UM, IF I CAN COMPETE IN
THE OLYMPICS, I WOULD, UH,
HOLD ON A SECOND.
THERE WE GO.
HOLD ON, SORRY, UM,
I THINK I WOULD DO THE LUGE
BECAUSE IT REQUIRES, I THINK,
THE LEAST AMOUNT OF PHYSICAL,
UH, ACUITY.
OKAY. THAT'S GREAT.
NOW, UH, I NEED YOU TO ADD
THE FIRST TWO GIVEN NUMBERS
AND THEN ADD THE NEXT NUMBER
TO THE LAST NUMBER GIVEN.
OKAY.
8 AND 7.
UM, 8 AND 7 EQUALS 15.
OKAY, 3.
UH, 10.
EXCELLENT. OKAY.
FOR THE NEXT TEST, I'M GOING TO
READ YOU A LIST OF WORDS
AND ASK YOU TO REPEAT THEM
IN REVERSE ORDER.
HOLD ON A SECOND.
NOW, THIS IS WHAT YOU MIGHT BE
WONDERING ABOUT THE COMPLEXITY
OF THE QUESTIONS WE ARE ASKING
EACH OTHER WHILE DRIVING.
FLAMETHROWER. FIRE HYDRANT.
WATER.
WHY AREN'T WE JUST READING
"WAR AND PEACE" OVER THE PHONE?
WATER. FIRE HYDRANT.
FLAMETHROWER.
WELL, EACH OF OUR QUESTIONS
FALLS INTO A CATEGORY THAT
ACTIVATES THE COGNITIVE PORTIONS
OF THE BRAIN.
GENERAL KNOWLEDGE --
WHICH COUNTRY HAS
THE LONGEST COASTLINE?
UH, THE LONGEST COASTLINE
OF ANY COUNTRY. CHINA?
ALL REQUIRE THE DRIVER TO USE
THE PART OF THEIR BRAIN
TO LISTEN AT THE SAME TIME
AS THEY'RE TRYING TO USE
ANOTHER PART OF
THEIR BRAIN TO DRIVE.
Narrator:
ADAM ISN'T BEING JUDGED ON
HOW WELL HE ANSWERS
THE QUESTIONS.
ADD 1 AND 7.
UH, HOLD ON.
[ LAUGHS ] THIS IS...
10.
Narrator: IT'S HOW WELL HE'S
DRIVING THAT'S THE ONLY METRIC.
OH! WHOA, WHOA.
Narrator: AND THE ANSWER TO THAT
IS NOT VERY WELL.
UM, HOLD ON. SORRY.
Narrator: THE COMBINATION OF
ONE HAND ON THE WHEEL
AND A BRAIN THAT'S MULTITASKING
INTO MELTDOWN MEANS THAT,
BY THE END OF THE TEST,
ADAM'S FLUNKED
WITH FLYING COLORS.
JAMIE, I'M DONE.
THAT WAS AWFUL. [ LAUGHS ]
[ LAUGHS ]
WELL, UH, LET'S RESET
AND SEE WHETHER
YOU'RE STILL A MENACE
ON THE NEXT ONE.
ALL RIGHT.
[ ENGINE SPUTTERING ]
- OKAY.
UM, [BLEEP].
WELL,
I'VE COMPLETED MY FIRST TEST,
AND TALKING ON THE PHONE
WAS ABSOLUTELY AWFUL.
AND THEN,
THE CAR STOPPED WORKING.
SO WE ARE ACTUALLY GOING TO
TRANSFER ALL OF THE CAMERAS
AND MICROPHONES FROM INSIDE
THIS CAR
TO ONE OF
OUR PRODUCTION VEHICLES.
AND I'M GONNA RUN THE TEST
A SECOND TIME, HANDS-FREE.
I MEAN, WE STILL CONSIDER
MY FIRST TEST VALID,
JUST HAVE TO DO THE SECOND ONE
IN A DIFFERENT CAR.
Narrator:
SO, WHILE THE TEAM PUSHES ON,
WHAT ELSE IS ON THE DOCKET?
SO DRIVING IN REVERSE.
PAINT ME A PICTURE.
WELL, LOOK,
OUR HERO, LET'S SAY,
IS DRIVING DOWN
A ONE WAY STREET.
HE THINKS HE'S HOME FREE,
BUT BLOCKING HIS PATH IS
A VILLAIN IN A CAR.
HE'S GOT NOWHERE TO GO,
SO USING THE ONLY AVENUE
OPEN TO HIM,
THE HERO THROWS THE CAR
INTO REVERSE AND BACKS UP,
BOBBING AND WEAVING THROUGH
TRAFFIC AT HIGH SPEED
TO EVENTUALLY
EVADE HIS CHASER.
AND YOU WANNA KNOW
IF THIS IS POSSIBLE.
I TOTALLY DO.
WE'VE BEEN TRAINED TO DRIVE
IN A LOT OF DIFFERENT WAYS
OVER THE YEARS, BUT BACKWARDS
ISN'T ONE OF THEM.
AND IT INVOLVES A LOT OF
DIFFERENT SKILLS,
NOT ONLY DRIVING ABILITY
AND SPATIAL AWARENESS BUT ALSO,
REALLY, PROPRIOCEPTION.
YEAH, YEAH.
LET'S GET TO DRIVING.
- OKAY.
BEAUTIFUL DAY.
WIDE-OPEN, EMPTY RUNWAY.
THE CONDITIONS ARE PERFECT.
OH, WAIT.
WE NEED A CAR.
[ TIRES SQUEAL ]
YOU ORDERED A CAR?
INDEED I DID, SIR.
PERFECT TIMING.
- [ LAUGHS ]
YOU KNOW, THE MOVIES ARE PACKED
WITH PEOPLE WHO CAN DRIVE WELL,
BUT THEY WOULD LEAD YOU TO
BELIEVE THAT YOU COULD DRIVE
FORWARD OR REVERSE,
HOWEVER YOU CHOOSE.
WE ARE CONSTANTLY SEEING
OUR MOVIE HEROES RACING AWAY
FROM THE BAD GUYS,
AVOIDING OBSTACLES,
AND DRIVING ALL OVER THE PLACE
WITH THE REAR END OF THE CAR
FACING THE DIRECTION
THAT THEY ARE ACTUALLY GOING.
Narrator: BUT BEFORE TRYING OUT
ANY TWISTS OR TURNS...
AND...THAT'S A QUARTER MILE.
Narrator:
THE GUYS FIRST WANT TO KNOW IF
CARS CAN EVEN REVERSE
HOLLYWOOD-FAST IN REAL LIFE.
AND FOR THAT, THEY'RE HITTING
THE STRAIGHTAWAY.
WE'VE SET UP A COURSE
THAT'S MEASURED.
AND WE'RE GONNA TEST OUT
THESE CARS,
SEE HOW FAST THEY GO
IN FORWARD
AND COMPARE THAT TO HOW FAST
THEY GO IN REVERSE.
ALL RIGHT, MR. HYNEMAN,
ARE YOU READY?
I'M GOOD TO GO.
ALL RIGHT,
COMMENCE QUARTER-MILE TEST
IN 3, 2, 1...GO.
[ TIRES SQUEAL ]
HERE IT COMES.
80 PER HOUR.
Narrator: IT'S A GOOD START
FOR THEIR CONVERTED CAB.
BUT HOW WILL THAT SPEED COMPARE
WHEN IT'S BACK-TO-FRONT?
MOST CARS THAT
YOU'RE EVER GONNA RUN INTO
HAVE ONLY ONE REVERSE GEAR,
WHICH MEANS THAT THE TOP SPEED
OF YOUR CAR IN REVERSE
IS ULTIMATELY LIMITED BY
THE REVERSE GEARING
AND THE SPEED AT WHICH
THE ENGINE IS TURNING OVER.
NOW, WILL OUR CAR
BE ABLE TO GO AS FAST
AS THEY SEEM TO GO IN
THE MOVIES?
THAT IS JUST WHAT
WE'RE ABOUT TO FIND OUT.
OKAY, COMMENCE BACKWARDS
QUARTER MILE IN 3, 2, 1...GO.
Narrator: JAMIE'S OFF.
BUT FROM THE GET-GO,
IT'S CLEAR THAT HE'S LESS
"FAST AND FURIOUS"...
...AND MORE
"DRIVING MISS DAISY."
BUT THAT'S BECAUSE HE'S USING
THIS RUN TO GET HIS EYE IN.
31 MILES PER HOUR.
I THINK HE CAN DO BETTER.
I THINK HE'S GOT MORE.
Narrator:
YUP, IT'S TEST TWO,
WHERE THE RUBBER WILL MEET
THE ROAD.
OKAY, ADAM, I'M IN PLACE
AND READY TO GO IN REVERSE.
Narrator:
AS JAMIE, THIS TIME,
PLANS TO PUT THE PEDAL
TO THE METAL.
ALL RIGHT, MR. HYNEMAN,
IN 3, 2, 1...GO.
49, 50, 52, 53.
54 MILES PER HOUR.
Narrator:
NOW, THAT'S MORE LIKE IT.
REACHING FREEWAY SPEEDS
IS MORE THAN A MATCH
FOR A HOLLYWOOD HERO,
BUT IT'S NOT ALL GOOD NEWS.
THE TRICK WITH DRIVING
AT HIGH SPEED IN REVERSE
WAS TO NOT DO VERY MUCH,
JUST KIND OF HOLD STILL
AND TRY AND KEEP THE CAR
IN A STRAIGHT LINE.
BUT UNFORTUNATELY, WE'RE NOT
GOING TO HAVE THAT OPTION NOW
BECAUSE, NOW WE'VE GOT TO DRIVE
THROUGH A SLALOM IN REVERSE.
AND THAT'S ALL ABOUT STEERING.
THAT'S GONNA BE REALLY HARD.
Narrator: STILL TO COME...
BYE, COP.
Narrator: BACKUP BOLOGNA
GETS A MOVIE MAKEOVER.
YEAH!
Narrator: AND...
- HELLO.
...HANDS-FREE GOES HIGH-TECH.
AHH!
[ LAUGHS ]
Narrator: IS DRIVING AT SPEED
IN REVERSE
AS EASY AS THE MOVIES MAKE OUT?
[ TIRES SQUEAL ]
WELL, NOT IF ADAM'S
STRAIGHT LINE TEST...
Jamie: COMING UP FAST.
Narrator:
...IS ANYTHING TO GO BY.
Adam: AHH!
[ TIRES SQUEAL ]
WHOA!
THERE ARE A COUPLE REASONS THAT
CARS ARE DIFFICULT TO DRIVE
AT HIGH SPEED IN REVERSE.
[ LAUGHS ] HEY. YEAH, YOU
STARTED TO LOSE IT AT ABOUT 50.
YEAH, MAN.
Jamie: AND THE FIRST IS THAT
THE STEERING IS NOT
SELF-CENTERING.
IF YOU LET GO OF THE WHEEL
OF A CAR GOING FORWARD
FOR JUST A SECOND,
IT'LL TEND TO SELF-CORRECT
BECAUSE OF THE OFFSET
OF THE WHEELS.
IF YOU'RE GOING IN REVERSE,
IT DOES THE OPPOSITE.
IF YOU LET GO OF THAT WHEEL,
YOU'RE GONNA GO HARD
TO THE SIDE,
AND YOU'RE GONNA DO A 180,
AND THAT'S DANGEROUS.
AND CORRECT A LITTLE TOO MUCH,
YOU'RE GONNA LOSE IT.
THE OTHER THING IS THAT
IT'S ALL ABOUT PERSPECTIVE.
WHEN YOU'RE GOING FORWARDS,
WITH YOUR HEAD IN ALIGN
WITH THE STEERING WHEEL,
DRIVING'S REALLY INTUITIVE.
BUT IN REVERSE, YOU'RE EITHER
LOOKING INTO THE MIRROR
OR OVER YOUR SHOULDER,
MEANING YOUR BRAIN'S HAVING TO
MAKE COMPLEX DECISIONS
FROM A VIEWPOINT
THAT IT'S JUST NOT USED TO.
[ TIRES SQUEAL ]
AND SO, WHEN THINGS GO WRONG,
YOU'RE GONNA FLIP THE CAR
OR SOMETHING BAD.
Narrator: GIVEN THEIR STRUGGLES
ON THE STRAIGHTAWAY,
TODAY'S TEST LOOKS TERRIFYING.
THIS IS WHAT WE CALL THE "DIVING
IN AT THE DEEP END" TEST.
WE'VE GOT A COURSE THAT'S FULL
OF THE KIND OF CHALLENGES
A HOLLYWOOD HERO HAS TO FACE,
AND WE'RE GOING TO SEE IF WE CAN
REVERSE THROUGH IT
AT HIGH SPEEDS WITHOUT CRASHING.
[ LAUGHS ]
THIS IS WHY WE HAVE INSURANCE.
Narrator: IT'S A COURSE THAT
A MOVIE MAESTRO
WOULD FINISH IN A FLASH.
BUT HOW WILL
THE MYTHBUSTERS MANAGE?
ALL RIGHT.
FIRST RUN IN 3, 2, 1...GO.
Narrator: ADAM'S OFF.
AND FROM THE OUTSET,
HE'S IGNORING THE MIRRORS...
WHOA.
OH, THERE GOES A CONE.
Narrator: AND GOING WITH
THE OVER-THE-SHOULDER TECHNIQUE.
AH, [BLEEP]!
Narrator: BUT IT'S HARDLY
PAYING DIVIDENDS.
BECAUSE NOT ONLY POOR STEERING
CRIPPLE HIS CONE COUNT...
AH.
Narrator: BUT HIS SLOW SPEED
MEANS HIS TIME IS TERRIBLE.
[ LAUGHS ]
HOW DID I DO?
1 MINUTE 7 SECONDS.
1 MINUTE, 7 SECONDS?
I'LL TELL YOU WHAT THAT DOES.
IT WREAKS HAVOC ON MY NECK.
WELL, I-I HAD A COUPLE OF
SCREWUPS ON THAT ONE.
IT'S VERY HARD TO GAUGE
HOW HARD YOU NEED TO
HIT A TURN IN REVERSE
BECAUSE ALL OF YOUR METRICS
FOR REACTION,
IN TERMS OF HOW THE CAR MOVES,
ARE WAY OFF-KILTER.
IT'S A FAR MORE SENSITIVE
DEVICE IN REVERSE.
Narrator: INDEED,
BUT CAN JAMIE MASTER THE METHOD
AND REVERSE
THIS MYTH'S FORTUNES?
[ ENGINE STARTS ]
ALL RIGHT, COWBOY.
HERE WE GO
IN 3, 2, 1...GO.
[ TIRES SQUEAL ]
[ LAUGHS ]
I LOVE THAT THIS IS OUR JOB.
Narrator: UNLIKE ADAM,
JAMIE'S USING THE MIRRORS
AND THE OVER-THE-SHOULDER
SYSTEM.
BUT IT'S NOT
A WINNING COMBINATION...
[ TIRES SQUEAL ]
[ LAUGHING ]
[ SHIFTS GEARS ]
Narrator:
BECAUSE HIS CRASH COURSE
IS EVEN WORSE THAN ADAM'S.
BUT EVENTUALLY,
HE CRAWLS TO THE FINISH LINE
IN A SLUGGISH 72 SECONDS...
[ TIRES SCREECH ]
[ LAUGHS ]
[ GROANS ]
Narrator: ...WHICH IS NOT
GOOD NEWS FOR THE MYTH.
OKAY, YOU WIN.
- [ LAUGHS ]
Narrator:
BUT ALL IS NOT LOST.
LOOK, THERE IS NO DOUBT THAT
THIS TEST WAS HARD.
AH!
THE COURSE WAS DIFFICULT,
AND WE ARE AT THE NOVICE END
OF THE REVERSE DRIVING SPECTRUM.
BUT WITH SOME EXPERT TRAINING,
WILL WE BE ABLE TO BRING THIS
MYTH BACK FROM THE BRINK?
THAT'S WHAT'S NEXT.
Narrator:
ACTUALLY, NOT QUITE.
BECAUSE NEXT, THE GUYS ARE
JUMPING SHIP BACK TO ALAMEDA
TO FIND OUT IF HANDS-FREE IS
AS DISTRACTING
AS HOLDING THE PHONE.
[ CELL PHONE RINGS ]
UH, HELLO, JAMIE.
Narrator: ADAM STARTED
WITH A HANDS-FULL CONTROL...
OH, WHOA. WHOA.
Narrator:
THAT WENT SO BADLY...
RIGHT.
Narrator:
HIS CAR REFUSED TO CONTINUE.
OKAY.
- [ ENGINE SPUTTERS ]
Narrator:
SO IT'S OUT WITH THE OLD.
ALL RIGHT, DAVE.
LET'S DO IT.
Narrator:
AND IN WITH THE NEW.
BUT WILL GOING HANDS-FREE
REALLY BE JUST AS BAD?
[ LINE RINGING ]
HERE WE GO.
[ BEEP ]
- WHY, HELLO, THIS IS ADAM.
WELL, HELLO THERE, ADAM.
Should I start driving?
Yes. Go ahead.
- OKAY.
Narrator: LIKE LAST TIME,
ADAM MUST COMPLETE THE COURSE
WHILE ANSWERING QUESTIONS
BOTH EASY...
OKAY, ON WHICH CONTINENT IS
THE SAHARA DESERT?
THE SAHARA DESERT IS ON
THE AFRICAN CONTINENT.
Narrator: AND HARD.
IF BUSTER WALKS HALFWAY
AROUND A CIRCLE
AND THEN TURNS AROUND
AND WALKS HALFWAY BACK,
IS HE NOW BACK
WHERE HE STARTED?
YES, HE IS.
NO, HE'S HALFWAY BACK.
[ Laughs ]
- AH.
OKAY.
Narrator: BUT DESPITE
THE OBVIOUS BURDEN ON HIS BRAIN,
HIS DRIVING HAS GOT BETTER.
AND ALTHOUGH A CLIPPED CONE
SEES HIM MARKED DOWN...
[ LAUGHING ]
- [ Laughs ]
SORRY.
I JUST HIT SOMETHING.
Narrator:
HIS FINAL SCORE HAS IMPROVED,
BUT WAS IT DUE TO THE PHONE?
Adam: WELL, I'VE COMPLETED
MY HANDS-FREE RUN
OF OUR DRIVING COURSE,
AND I DID IT A LOT BETTER.
BUT HERE'S THE THING,
I FOUND TAKING THE QUESTIONS
FROM JAMIE JUST AS DISTRACTING
AS I DID THE FIRST TIME.
I FEEL LIKE MY BETTER
PERFORMANCE ON THE SECOND TEST
COULD BE CHALKED UP TO JUST
UNDERSTANDING THE COURSE
A LITTLE BIT BETTER.
BUT THAT'S WHY JAMIE'S
GONNA START HANDS-FREE
AND THEN GO TO HANDS-FULL.
IF THAT IS IN EFFECT,
WE SHOULD CANCEL IT OUT
BY CHANGING THE ORDER
THAT WE DO THE TEST IN.
THAT'S THE THEORY, ANYWAY.
WANT TO SEE
WHAT YOU CAN DO WITH IT.
I'M GONNA SUCK.
I CAN TELL YOU ALREADY.
Narrator: NOT ONLY WILL JAMIE
INCREASE THEIR SAMPLE SIZE,
BUT BY GOING HANDS-FREE FIRST...
JAMIE AND I ALMOST NEVER
ACTUALLY SPEAK ON THE PHONE.
SO THIS ACTUALLY HAS A BIT OF
NOVELTY TO ME.
Narrator:
THE GUYS ARE TRYING TO ELIMINATE
ANY COURSE-LEARNING BIAS.
[ LINE RINGING ]
THIS IS JAMIE.
AH, GOOD AFTERNOON, JAMIE.
IT'S ADAM.
Go ahead and start driving,
and I'm going to start
asking you some questions.
Narrator: ADAM STARTS
WITH A SIMPLE ICEBREAKER.
ALL RIGHT, HEY, JAMIE,
IF YOU COULD WAKE UP TOMORROW
AND GAIN ANY SINGLE
QUALITY OR ABILITY,
WHAT WOULD IT BE AND WHY?
UM, I COULD FLY.
WHY?
Narrator: BUT EVEN THAT PROVES
TOO MUCH FOR JAMIE.
WELL, UH,
BECAUSE THEN I COULD GO, UM...
WHAT WAS THE QUESTION AGAIN?
WHY WOULD YOU LIKE TO FLY?
UH, WELL, BECAUSE,
THAT WOULD, UH,
IT WOULD SAVE A LOT OF
GASOLINE ACTUALLY.
AND, UH, YOU KNOW,
I COULD, UH,
OH, LOOK AT THAT.
I BUMPED OVER
A WHOLE BUNCH OF THINGS.
[ LAUGHS ]
Narrator: WITH NO IMPROVEMENT
OVER THE REST OF THE COURSE...
I'D LIKE YOU TO ADD
THE NUMBERS 4 AND 7.
LET'S SEE.
UH, 4 AND 7, UH...
Uh...
TICKTOCK, GRANDPA.
10 -- OR, NO, 11.
Narrator: JAMIE SCORES
THE WORST RESULT OF THE DAY --
A DISAPPOINTING 66.
THAT WAS AWESOME.
HE STARTS EVERY ANSWER
WITH, "LET'S SEE." [ LAUGHS ]
I'M SURE I WAS DOING
THE SAME THINGS,
BUT IT'S JUST VERY ENJOYABLE TO
LISTEN TO SOMEONE SO DISTRACTED.
Narrator:
A QUICK RESET LATER,
[ CELL PHONE RINGS ]
AND THEY'RE SET FOR
THE FOURTH AND FINAL RUN...
HELLO.
ALL RIGHT.
START YOUR DRIVING.
Narrator:
JAMIE, HANDS-FULL.
I'm going to read you
a list of words
and ask you to repeat them
in a reverse order.
CRASH, BURN, DEMOLISH.
UH, DEMOLISH, UH, BURN, CRASH.
E.M.T., AMBULANCE, DOCTOR.
THERE'S QUITE A NARRATIVE
IMPLIED BY THESE.
DOCTOR, AMBULANCE, E.M.T.
- YES.
Narrator: DESPITE HAVING ONLY
ONE HAND ON THE WHEEL
AND SWAPPING THE PHONE
MID-DRIVE, JAMIE SCORES 72,
A FAIL BY SOME DISTANCE,
BUT AN IMPROVEMENT NONETHELESS.
SO, WHAT DOES THIS MEAN
FOR THE MYTH?
OKAY, NOW,
FOR THIS MYTH TO BE TRUE,
JAMIE'S HANDS-FREE SCORE HAD TO
MATCH HIS HANDS-FULL SCORE.
AND SO DID MINE.
BUT THAT DIDN'T QUITE HAPPEN.
GRAPHICS, HELP ME OUT.
YOU CAN SEE THAT I DROVE BETTER
HANDS-FREE,
WHILE JAMIE DROVE
BETTER HANDS-FULL.
BUT THAT DATA ALSO SHOWS
THAT WE BOTH IMPROVED ON
OUR SECOND RUNS BECAUSE WE HAD
EXPERIENCE OF THE COURSE.
NOW, IF WE REMOVE THAT BIAS BY
AVERAGING JAMIE'S AND MY DATA,
WHAT DO WE GET?
BEAUTIFUL,
NEAR-IDENTICAL SCORES
FOR EACH OF THE TWO TECHNIQUES.
BUT WE ARE NOT DONE YET,
FOR TWO PARTICULAR REASONS.
ONE, OUR COURSE
ISN'T VERY REAL-WORLD.
FOR STARTERS,
THERE'S NO TRAFFIC.
SECOND,
AND PERHAPS MORE IMPORTANTLY,
IS JAMIE'S
AND MY DRIVING ABILITIES.
WE HAVE BOTH RECEIVED
TONS OF TRAINING OVER THE YEARS
IN LOTS OF DIFFERENT
DRIVING TECHNIQUES.
WHOA!
WHOO, YEAH!
WE ARE QUITE FAR
FROM YOUR AVERAGE JOES,
AND THAT IS WHAT WE NEED NEXT.
AAH!
3, 2, 1...GO.
[ TIRES SQUEAL ]
Adam: NOW, JAMIE AND I HAVE
ALREADY GONE PRETTY FAR,
TEACHING OURSELVES THE RUDIMENTS
OF DRIVING IN REVERSE.
[ TIRES SQUEAL ]
[ LAUGHS ]
BUT IF WE'RE GONNA GET
REALLY GOOD AT THIS,
WE'RE GONNA NEED TO
GET TRAINED BY AN EXPERT.
LUCKILY, WE HAVE AN EXPERT
IN REVERSE TACTICAL DRIVING
RIGHT HERE.
HELLO, SIR. HELLO.
Jamie:
BRIAN FRAZER IS A TRAINER
AT THE EMERGENCY VEHICLE
OPERATIONS COURSE
HERE IN CALIFORNIA.
NOW, WE'VE USED HIM REPEATEDLY
OVER PAST YEARS,
WHENEVER WE'VE HAD TO LEARN
HOW TO DEAL WITH A PARTICULARLY
DIFFICULT DRIVING SITUATION.
AND DRIVING AT SPEED
IN REVERSE CERTAINLY QUALIFIES.
ALL RIGHT, BRIAN.
WHERE DO WE START?
WE'RE GOING TO PUT BARREL HERE,
TWO BARRELS HERE,
ONE ON EACH SIDE OF THE CAR.
ALL RIGHT.
Narrator: BRIAN'S FIRST JOB IS
TO IGNORE THE CURRENT COURSE...
RIGHT THERE IS GOOD.
GOOD. GOOD ENDING POINT.
AW.
THIS IS WHY WE CAN'T HAVE
NICE THINGS.
Narrator: AND SET UP SOMETHING
WAY MORE STRAIGHTFORWARD...
ALL RIGHT, THAT'S THE COURSE.
NOW WHAT DO WE DO?
DRIVE IT.
- OKAY. LET'S GO.
Narrator: BECAUSE THE TECHNIQUE
HE'S GOING TO TEACH
IS SURPRISINGLY SIMPLE.
SO I'M GONNA CHANGE
MY SEATING POSITION NOW
A LITTLE BIT.
- OKAY.
I'M GOING TO PROP MYSELF UP,
LOOSEN MY SEAT BELT.
TURN YOURSELF AS FAR AS
YOU CAN AROUND.
GET YOUR BODY ALMOST IN
THE CENTER OF THE -- OF THE CAR.
OKAY.
I'M GONNA STEER THE CAR NOW
WITH ONE HAND.
BUT THIS HAND WILL NEVER LEAVE
THE STEERING WHEEL.
NOT -- YOU'RE NOT GONNA LET
THE STEERING WHEEL
SHIFT IN YOUR HAND TO LOCK.
YOU'RE -- YOU'RE PALMING
THE WHEEL THE ENTIRE TIME.
I SEE. OKAY, COOL.
Narrator:
AND BELIEVE IT OR NOT,
THAT'S APPARENTLY
ALL THERE IS TO IT.
3, 2, 1...GO.
Narrator: BY SHIFTING HIS BODY
TO THE CENTER OF THE CAR...
[ LAUGHS ] OH, WOW!
Narrator: AND KEEPING ONE HAND
ON THE WHEEL AT ALL TIMES...
WOW, I CAN'T BELIEVE HOW FAST
YOU'RE ABLE TO DO THIS.
Narrator:
BRIAN SPEEDS THROUGH THE COURSE
AT AN IMPRESSIVE
41 MILES PER HOUR.
THAT IS AMAZING.
Adam: SO BRIAN JUST SHOWED ME
THAT SOMETHING I THOUGHT WAS
IMPOSSIBLE IS IN FACT,
TOTALLY POSSIBLE.
SO I'M ABOUT TO GIVE THAT
A SHOT.
THIS IS GONNA BE COOL.
Narrator: LIKE BRIAN,
ADAM SLIDES TO THE CENTER
TO GIVE A VIEWPOINT
THAT'S EASIER TO PROCESS.
OH, LOOK AT THAT.
- YEAH.
OKAY, SO. ALL RIGHT.
3, 2, 1...
Narrator: AND LIKE BRIAN,
HE THEN NAILS THE COURSE.
OH, THAT'S SO COOL.
Narrator: TO CHECK IT WASN'T
JUST BEGINNER'S LUCK,
HE TRIES AGAIN
AND GOES EVEN FASTER.
AWESOME.
Jamie: I GOT TO SAY,
THIS IS AMAZING.
WHEN WE GOT HERE THIS MORNING,
I THOUGHT ADAM WAS GONNA BE
TRAINING FOR FOUR, FIVE,
MAYBE SIX HOURS.
BUT IT'S NOT BEEN
LIKE THAT AT ALL.
INSTEAD,
IN JUST 20 MINUTES,
HE'S GONE FROM BEING PRETTY
AVERAGE TO BEING PRETTY GREAT.
AND IT SEEMS TO BE ALL DOWN TO
THE CENTRAL HEAD POSITION,
WHICH SEEMS TO BE LETTING
ADAM'S BRAIN PROCESS
THE DIRECTION TO TURN
MUCH MORE ACCURATELY.
SO, WE'RE GONNA PUT HIM BACK ON
OUR ORIGINAL COURSE TO SEE
HOW HE DOES NOW.
SHOULD BE INTERESTING.
Narrator: IT'S THE COURSE
THE GUYS COULDN'T CRACK.
SO, YOU READY TO PUT WHAT YOU
LEARNED INTO PRACTICE?
I AM. IN FACT, I CAN'T WAIT TO
TRY THIS COURSE NOW.
3, 2, 1...GO.
Narrator: BUT WILL
HIS 20 MINUTES OF TRAINING
LET ADAM TURN IT AROUND?
HE'S OFF TO A GOOD START.
TURNS ARE A LOT
SMOOTHER THIS TIME.
HE'S LOOKING REALLY GOOD.
YEAH!
WELL, YEAH.
HE'S MOVING PRETTY QUICK.
COMING IN GOOD.
YEAH!
TELL ME, TELL ME, TELL ME,
TELL ME, TELL ME, TELL ME.
TELL ME, TELL ME HOW I DID.
57.25.
BOOM! THAT WAS COOL.
Narrator: IT'S CLOSE TO
AN ASTOUNDING RESULT.
WITH JUST TWO MINOR
MODIFICATIONS...
Adam: YEAH!
Narrator: ADAM'S BETTERED
HIS BEST BY OVER 15%.
ALL RIGHT, GUESS IT'S TIME TO
BRING ON THE NEXT EVENT.
[ TIRES SQUEAL ]
Narrator:
AND WHAT THAT MEANS IS,
IT'S TIME FOR SOME
REAL-LIFE MOVIE MAYHEM.
BUT FIRST...
HOLD THE PHONE...
BECAUSE,
IN DRIVING DISTRACTED,
NEITHER ADAM NOR JAMIE
COULD DRIVE SAFELY
WHILE TALKING HANDS-FREE.
BUT NOW, IN A LOCATION WAY
MORE SOPHISTICATED...
[ LAUGHS ] IT'S LOCKED.
Narrator:
IT'S TIME TO UP THE ANTE.
JAMIE AND I HAVE REALIZED
WE NEED MUCH MORE CONTROLLED,
SCIENTIFIC
AND REALISTIC CONDITIONS,
WHICH IS WHY WE'VE COME HERE TO
ENLIST THE HELP OF THE EXPERTS
AT THE STANFORD UNIVERSITY
AUTOMOTIVE INNOVATION FACILITY.
WHEN WE ASKED FOR THEIR HELP
IN GETTING MORE REALISTIC,
THEY SHOWED US A VIRTUAL WORLD.
COME HERE.
THIS IS THEIR STATE-OF-THE-ART
DRIVING SIMULATOR.
IT IS AWESOME.
FROM THE FRONT SEAT OF THIS CAR,
YOU ARE COMPLETELY IMMERSED
IN A WORLD CONTROLLED
AND DESIGNED BY A COMPUTER,
INTO WHICH WE CAN ADD
ALL SORTS OF TRAFFIC,
PEDESTRIANS, OBSTACLES,
AND SURPRISES FOR ALL OF OUR
TEST SUBJECTS, THAT'S RIGHT,
MANY, MANY TEST SUBJECTS,
WHILE WE GET TO THE BOTTOM OF
THIS MYTH.
Narrator: IT'S A MULTI-MILLION
DOLLAR MACHINE...
ALL RIGHT, THEN.
GOING FOR A DRIVE
IN THE SIMULATOR.
Narrator: WHICH JAMIE
CAN'T RESIST TURNING UP TO 11.
[ Strained voice ]
OKAY, HERE WE GO.
[ LAUGHS ]
[ HORN HONKS ]
I'M GONNA GO THE OTHER WAY.
WHOA. THIS IS CRAZY.
AH... [ IMITATES CRASH SOUND ]
[ LAUGHS ]
CRAZY DRIVING ASIDE,
THIS DRIVING SIMULATOR IS
ACTUALLY VERY GOOD.
YEAH, GET OUT OF MY WAY.
[ LAUGHS ]
[ HORN HONKING ]
THE WAY THE SCREEN WRAPS AROUND,
THE VISUALS ARE
CONVINCING ENOUGH
THAT YOU HAVE TO REMIND YOURSELF
THAT THIS ISN'T
A REAL DRIVING SCENARIO.
HE'S DOING, LIKE, 95.
INTERESTING.
I'LL SEE HOW HE LIKES THIS.
[ HORN BLARES ]
IN FACT, IT'S SO GOOD THAT
I WAS STARTING
TO GET A LITTLE CARSICK.
SO I THINK, AS FAR AS
TESTING DISTRACTED DRIVING,
IT'S AS GOOD A SIMULATION
AS WE'RE GOING TO GET.
Narrator:
AS WELL AS THE FREEWAY...
[ LAUGHING ]
Narrator: THERE'S ALSO
A DETAILED CITYSCAPE...
[ LAUGHS ] OH, I GUESS
I BETTER PUT IT IN REVERSE.
Narrator: ...SO THAT ALL
DRIVING ENVIRONMENTS ARE TESTED.
[ JAMIE LAUGHS ]
Narrator:
THE 30 VOLUNTEER DRIVERS
WILL BE JUDGED ON WHETHER
THEY PAY ATTENTION
TO THE GPS INSTRUCTIONS...
<i>Automated Male Voice:</i>
<i>AT THE NEXT INTERSECTION,</i>
<i>TURN LEFT.</i>
Narrator: ...AND WHETHER OR NOT
THEY CRASH.
[ TIRES SQUEAL ]
AH!
Narrator:
BUT THAT'S NOT THE ONLY DATA,
BECAUSE DRIVERS WILL ALSO WEAR
THE LATEST
IN EYE-TRACKING TECHNOLOGY.
THIS EYE-TRACKING SYSTEM RECORDS
PRECISELY WHERE AND HOW LONG
I'M LOOKING AT SOMETHING.
NOW, THAT'S GONNA GIVE US
HARD DATA AS TO THE LEVEL OF
DISTRACTION THAT I'M
EXPERIENCING WHILE I'M DRIVING.
Narrator: WITH EAGLE-EYED JAMIE
ALL WIRED UP,
HE'S GOING TO BE THE FIRST
DATA OF THE DAY...
ALL RIGHT.
CALLING HIM NOW.
[ CELL PHONE RINGING ]
Narrator:
STARTING AFTER THE BREAK.
HELLO?
Narrator: USING A PHONE
ON THE ROAD IS BAD NEWS,
BUT IS GOING HANDS-FREE
JUST AS FOOLISH?
TO FIND OUT,
THE MYTHBUSTERS HAVE A SIMULATOR
THAT'S SECOND TO NONE...
[ LAUGHS ] I LOVE THIS THING.
ALL RIGHT.
CALLING HIM NOW.
Narrator: AND A HYNEMAN
THAT'S GOT HIS HANDS FULL.
HELLO?
- Good morning, Mr. Hyneman.
ARE YOU READY TO START
THIS TEST?
I'M READY.
- OKAY.
Kick the car into drive,
start driving,
AND I'LL START ASKING
YOU SOME QUESTIONS.
Narrator: THE QUESTIONS ARE
SIMILAR TO THOSE POSED BEFORE.
DID YOU PLAY A MUSICAL
INSTRUMENT AS A CHILD, JAMIE?
YEAH, I HAD A-A TUBA
IN THE BATHROOM
RIGHT NEXT TO THE TOILET
THAT I WOULD PLAY WHEN I WAS,
YOU KNOW, DOING NUMBER TWO
OR SOMETHING.
[ LAUGHS ]
Narrator: BUT WHAT'S INTERESTING
IS THAT, ON THE FREEWAY...
SPEED, UNDERWATER, CAMERA.
Narrator:
JAMIE'S DRIVING...
HOLD ON. YOU KNOW, SOMEBODY JUST
PULLED IN FRONT OF ME.
Narrator:
AND ANSWERS...
CAMERA, UNDERWATER, SPEED.
Narrator:
ARE SURPRISINGLY SOLID.
IN FACT, IT'S ONLY
WHEN HE HITS THE STREETS...
12 AND 7.
Narrator:
THAT HE STARTS TO WAVER.
OKAY, UH, LET'S SEE.
UH, 19.
Narrator:
WITH SO MANY DISTRACTIONS,
IT'S NO SURPRISE WHEN JAMIE
TAKES A TURN FOR THE WORSE.
<i>Automated male voice:</i>
<i>AT THE NEXT INTERSECTION,</i>
<i>TURN LEFT.</i>
[ SIGNAL CLICKING ]
Jamie,
you have taken a wrong turn,
AND THAT MEANS THAT
THE TEST IS OVER.
YOU HAVE FAILED.
OKAY.
Narrator:
WITH NO REST FOR THE WICKED,
JAMIE IMMEDIATELY MOVES ON TO
THE HANDS-FREE TEST.
HELLO.
What is the longest running race
in the Olympic Games called?
THE LONGEST RUNNING RACE IN, UH,
IN THE OLYMPIC GAME IS
CALLED A MARADON.
A MARADON?
- MARADON.
YOU MEAN MARATHON?
- YEAH.
OKAY.
Narrator: ONCE AGAIN,
JAMIE'S FOCUSED ON THE FREEWAY
BUT STRUGGLES IN THE CITY
AS HIS BRAIN TRIES TO PROCESS
THE TRAFFIC
AND THE CONVERSATION.
THE EARTH IS LOCATED
IN WHAT GALAXY?
UH, THE, UM...
You know, I don't know
the answer to that question.
Narrator:
LIKE LAST TIME...
<i>Automated male voice:</i>
<i>AT THE NEXT INTERSECTION,</i>
<i>TURN LEFT.</i>
Narrator:
JAMIE DOESN'T CRASH,
BUT HE DOES IGNORE THE GPS...
OH, I'M SORRY.
I SCREWED THIS UP.
Narrator:
...MEANING HE'S FAILED AGAIN.
WELL, THE LONG AND THE SHORT
OF IT IS THAT JAMIE HAS DONE
THIS TEST TWICE
IN OUR VIRTUAL ENVIRONMENT,
ONCE HOLDING THE PHONE,
ONCE HANDS-FREE,
AND HE HAS FAILED BOTH TIMES.
IT'S LOOKING PRETTY GOOD
FOR THIS MYTH,
BUT WE ARE NOT LEAVING IT HERE.
NO, NO, NO.
WE'RE GOING TO FUNNEL
A WHOLE BUNCH OF VOLUNTEERS
THROUGH THIS TESTING PROCEDURE
TO GET SOME REAL NUMBERS
TO BACK UP
OUR POTENTIAL CONCLUSION.
Narrator: FIRST OF
THE 30 VOLUNTEERS IS TIFFANY,
WHO WILL BE DRIVING
HANDS-FULL.
THE FIRST THING I WANT TO KNOW
IS WHAT MUSICAL INSTRUMENT
YOU PLAYED AS A CHILD.
NONE.
Narrator: ON THE FREEWAY,
HER DRIVING IS SOLID...
LOGIC QUESTIONS.
Narrator:
AND HER ANSWERS ARE PERFECT.
Name four days that start
with the letter "T."
TODAY, TOMORROW, TUESDAY,
AND THURSDAY.
EXCELLENT.
Narrator: BUT MOMENTS
AFTER HITTING THE CITY...
HOW MUCH DIRT IS --
OH, WE JUST RAN DOWN
A CYCLIST.
THIS TEST IS OVER.
[ LINE RINGING ]
Narrator:
NEXT UP IS MICHAEL.
HELLO?
Narrator: AND, HANDS-FREE,
HE'S FINE ON THE FREEWAY...
WHAT IS SOMETHING YOU HAVE AT
HOME THAT YOU SHOULD THROW AWAY,
BUT YOU CAN'T?
AH, MY OLD COMPUTER.
I STILL HAVE ONE THAT
GOT BUILT IN, LIKE, '95.
Narrator:
BUT DEADLY DOWNTOWN.
UM, WHICH COUNTRY --
[ TIRES SQUEAL ]
OH! AHH.
I-I BELIEVE THAT MIGHT BE
THE END OF OUR TEST THERE,
MICHAEL.
WHERE DID THAT COME FROM?
[ LAUGHS ]
THANK YOU VERY MUCH, SIR.
[ BLEEP ]
Narrator:
WHEN THE NEXT FOUR VOLUNTEERS
ALSO CRASH AND BURN...
AH!
Narrator:
IT'S LOOKING GOOD FOR THE MYTH.
STOP THE CAR AND, PLEASE,
LICENSE AND REGISTRATION, MA'AM.
Narrator:
AND ALTHOUGH DRIVER SEVEN
DOES MAKE IT THROUGH
THE COURSE INTACT...
ALL RIGHT,
UH, CONGRATULATIONS.
YOU HAVE SUCCESSFULLY
COMPLETED THE TEST.
Narrator:
NEARLY ALL OTHER DRIVERS,
WHATEVER THEIR PHONE FASHION,
EITHER GET LOST...
UH, RON, I'M SORRY TO INFORM YOU
THAT YOU HAVE NOW MISSED A TURN.
AND THUS, THE TEST IS OVER.
Narrator: ...OR WORSE.
OH, WE HAD A CRASH,
DIDN'T WE?
Narrator: UNDETERRED,
THE GUYS PLOW ON
THROUGH TWO FULL DAYS OF
TESTING.
AND WHEN VOLUNTEER 30
TAKES DRAMATIC EVASIVE ACTION...
[ LAUGHS ] I SUCK AT THIS.
Narrator: THE GUYS HAVE ALL
THE DATA THEY COULD HOPE FOR.
ALL RIGHT,
WE HAVE RUN A LOT OF VOLUNTEERS
THROUGH THIS EXPERIMENT,
AND WE'VE GOT A LOT OF DATA
TO TAKE A LOOK AT.
SO IT'S TIME TO LEAVE
THIS VIRTUAL WORLD,
DRIVE THROUGH THE REAL WORLD,
BACK TO OUR SHOP,
AND CRUNCH THE NUMBERS.
NO WAY.
THEY SAID THAT?
THAT IS HILARIOUS.
HOLD ON JUST A SECOND.
WHAT?
WE WERE WAITING FOR THE RESULTS
ON DISTRACTED DRIVING.
OH, OKAY.
UH, I GOT TO CALL YOU BACK.
[ BEEP ]
- YES, WE HAVE RESULTS.
WE TESTED 30 DRIVERS OUT
IN STANFORD, 15 HANDS-FULL,
15 HANDS-FREE.
HERE IS THE RESULT.
Uh, HANDS-FULL -- ONE PASSED,
FIVE FAILED BY DRIVING THE WRONG
WAY, NINE FAILED BY CRASHING.
HANDS-FREE -- ONE PASSED,
SIX FAILED BY GETTING LOST,
AND EIGHT FAILED BY CRASHING.
WHAT'S THAT MEAN
STATISTICALLY?
STATISTICALLY,
IT MEANS NO DIFFERENCE.
AND WHAT ABOUT EYE TRACKING?
THE EYE TRACKER
WAS VERY INTERESTING.
ACROSS ALL 30 DRIVERS,
THE AMOUNT OF TIME THEY SPENT
LOOKING AT SOMETHING
OTHER THAN THE ROAD
WAS IDENTICAL BETWEEN
HANDS-FREE AND HANDS-FULL.
WELL, THERE YOU HAVE IT.
[ CELL PHONE BEEPS ]
DON'T USE YOUR CELL PHONE
WHILE YOU'RE DRIVING.
YEAH, I'M DONE. OKAY.
SO, WHERE DO YOU WANT TO
MEET FOR LUNCH? ABSOLUTELY.
Narrator: COMING RIGHT UP,
THE GUYS REV IN REVERSE...
YEAH!
Narrator:
FOR A CONFOUNDING CONCLUSION.
[ TIRES SQUEAL ]
AH!
Narrator: IN DRIVING IN REVERSE,
THERE'S A PROBLEM.
WE -- WE CAN'T CATCH
A BREAK TODAY.
WE JUST ROLLED UP THE WINDOWS
'CAUSE THE WIND'S
SO DIABOLICAL,
AND WE LOCKED THE KEYS INSIDE.
[ LAUGHS ]
Narrator: LUCKILY, FOR ONCE,
THERE'S A COP AROUND
WHEN YOU NEED HIM.
HEY!
- BINGO.
[ LAUGHS ]
MYTHBUSTERS,
REPOSSESSING CARS SINCE 1979.
[ TIRES SQUEAL ]
IT'S ALL ABOUT REVERSE DRIVING
IN THIS EPISODE,
AND HOW EASY IT IS VERSUS HOW
EASY HOLLYWOOD MAKES IT SEEM.
WHOA!
JAMIE AND I HAVE TRIED OUT
SOME COURSES OURSELVES.
[ TIRES SQUEAL ]
[ LAUGHS ]
WE'VE BEEN TRAINED BY A COP
WHO IS AN EXPERT
IN DRIVING IN REVERSE.
HERE WE GO. 3, 2...
THE REVERSE.
- OH.
THERE WE GO.
- THANK YOU. [ LAUGHS ]
SO NOW, IT'S TIME FOR ME
TO TAKE ALL OF THE SKILLS
I'VE THUS FAR LEARNED
AND PUT THEM TO A REAL TEST.
I'M HERE AT
AN ABANDONED NEIGHBORHOOD
IN MARINA, CALIFORNIA, WHERE MY
CREW HAS SET UP A COURSE,
AND I'M JUST SUPPOSED TO DRIVE
AS FAST AS I CAN IN REVERSE.
I'M ACTUALLY PRETTY CURIOUS
HOW THIS IS GONNA TURN OUT.
Narrator: THIS FINAL FAREWELL IS
A HALF MILE OF TWISTS AND TURNS.
BUT IT'S GOT A WHOLE LOT
MORE BESIDES...
AS THE GUYS HAVE PUT THE MOVIE
MAYHEM BACK INTO THIS MYTH.
AND THAT'S NOT JUST THE PROPS.
WE'RE GONNA PUT A LITTLE
PRESSURE ON ADAM,
BECAUSE I'M GONNA BE
IN A COP CAR
ON HIS ASS THE WHOLE WAY,
WITH THE SOLE EXCEPTION THAT,
WHEN HE SEES ME AND TAKES OFF,
I'M GONNA BE OUTSIDE MY CAR.
SO HE'S GONNA HAVE JUST
A LITTLE BIT OF A HEAD START.
Narrator: ADAM'S GOAL,
LIKE THE CLASSIC HOLLYWOOD HERO,
IS TO MAKE IT TO THE FINISH LINE
BEFORE THOSE PESKY POLICE.
THAT IS A COP.
THAT'S BAD.
Narrator: BUT WITH REVERSE GEAR
HIS ONLY OPTION,
WILL HE ESCAPE TO VICTORY?
HERE WE GO. BYE, COP.
[ TIRES SQUEAL ]
Narrator: THE CHASE IS ON.
HERE WE GO.
GETTIN' THE HECK OUTTA HERE.
Narrator: AND BY THE TIME
JAMIE'S GOT GOING,
ADAM'S ALREADY OUT OF SIGHT.
MAKE A RIGHT-HAND TURN HERE.
DON'T LET GO OF THAT WHEEL.
Narrator: BY SHIFTING TO
THE CENTRAL POSITION,
HE'S ABLE TO NAVIGATE
WITH SKILL.
WHOA. FLAMING CAR! DUDE.
OH, MAN.
POST-APOCALYPSE.
Narrator:
AT LEAST, WHEN HE WANTS TO.
I WANT THOSE BOXES.
COME ON. YEAH!
Narrator: BUT WHILE HIS STEERING
IS SUPREME...
I DON'T KNOW WHERE HE IS.
I HOPE HE'S NOT CLOSE.
Narrator: HIS SPEED, WHILE FAST,
IS NO MATCH FOR JAMIE.
OH, FRUIT STAND.
I'M NOT GONNA MISS
THE FRUIT STAND.
WHOA! AAH. OH! [ LAUGHS ]
Narrator: ADAM MAY BE DOWN,
BUT HE'S NOT OUT,
AS HE REVERSES BACK UPHILL...
AH, I'M GOING STILL!
Narrator: A STRATEGY THAT
THE HYNEMAN THEN COPIES.
WITH BOTH DRIVERS NOW REVVING
IN REVERSE,
IT'S A CASE OF WHO'S GONNA
BLINK FIRST.
[ TIRES SQUEAL ]
OH! [ LAUGHS ]
OH.
YET ANOTHER IN THE LONG LINE OF
THINGS THAT WE SHOULD JUST
SET UP FOR THE PUBLIC
AND CHARGE MONEY FOR.
THAT WAS AWESOME.
STEP OUT OF THE CAR
WITH YOUR HANDS UP.
OKAY. [ LAUGHS ]
THAT WAS SO MUCH FUN.
- [ LAUGHS ]
OH, MY GOD.
THAT WAS THE BEST THING EVER.
WELL, THAT WENT PRETTY MUCH AS
GOOD AS I COULD HAVE IMAGINED.
FIRST OFF,
THE COURSE WAS AMAZING,
FULL OF ALL SORTS OF
REALLY INTERESTING OBSTACLES,
FROM FRUIT STANDS TO DUDES
FIXING THEIR CARS TO,
COME ON, A FLAMING CAR.
I ALSO WAS ABLE TO GO THROUGH IT
REALLY FAST, I MEAN,
FAST ENOUGH WHERE I ALMOST LOST
CONTROL OF THE CAR ON A COUPLE
OF THE STRAIGHTAWAYS.
LIKE, IT STARTED FISHTAILING.
BUT BECAUSE OF BRIAN'S TRAINING,
I WAS ABLE TO BRING THE CAR
BACK UNDER CONTROL.
OH, OH, ALMOST LOST
A LITTLE CONTROL THERE.
THEN, I ACTUALLY SPUN OUT
WHEN JAMIE HIT ME.
BUT AGAIN, IN REVERSE,
I BOLTED BACK UP THE HILL.
AND JAMIE CHASED ME, AND IT WAS
ALL GOING PRETTY GOOD.
BUT I WAS GOING TOO FAST ON
THE ACCELERATOR AND I SPUN OUT.
HE JAMMED INTO MY FRONT WHEEL,
AND I COULD NOT MOVE.
TEST OVER.
SO HOW DO YOU WANNA CALL IT?
I HAVE TO SAY,
I STARTED THIS STORY
THINKING IT WAS GONNA BE
HANDILY BUSTED.
AND I AM NOW THINKING THAT
IT'S ACTUALLY PLAUSIBLE,
THAT IT'S NOT UNREASONABLE
HOW MUCH SPEED
AND MANEUVERABILITY YOU CAN GET
GOING IN REVERSE.
YEAH, I MEAN, BOTH OF US,
I THINK,
IF WE HAD OUR CHOICE WOULD GO,
YOU KNOW, FRONT FORWARD, UM,
'CAUSE THAT'S GONNA BE
YOUR BETTER OPTION.
BUT IT'S SURPRISING
HOW GOOD IT CAN BE.
LET'S CALL IT PLAUSIBLE.
ALL RIGHT.
I'M GONNA DRIVE FORWARD HOME,
THOUGH.
IF YOU CAN.
- [ LAUGHS ]