[ Radio chatter ]
[ Squeaks ]
[ Whirring ]
Aah!
Sorry about that.
These things are
a little tricky to fly.
Yeah, well, I swear,
with a slightly larger one,
you could do some
genuine damage, like,
maybe even kill somebody.
Wait a minute...
[ Muttering ]
Let's start the show.
-- Captions by vitac --
www.Vitac.Com
captions paid for by
Discovery Communications
[ whirring ]
I'm guess this story's
about drones.
It is, in fact, we have two
awesome flying stories
in this episode.
One of them is about
these guys.
But first up, we have
a totally amazing story.
Let me ask you,
do the words "Dragon Lady"
mean anything to you?
I don't wanna
talk about it.
Okay, I think, we're probably
thinking of different things.
'Cause "Dragon Lady" is,
in fact, the nickname
for the legendary
high-altitude single-seater
u-2 reconnaissance plane
in use by the air force
since the late '50s.
[ Radio chatter ]
Okay, what about it?
Well, there is a myth
that the u-2 plane
is the toughest plane
to fly and to land
of any other plane.
[ Man speaking indistinctly
over radio ]
And I think we should
take a close look at that.
The air force
isn't gonna let us
get anywhere near
something like that.
Man: C1, 34.8, 34.8.
I thought the same thing,
but amazingly,
they have agreed to let
you and I have a close-up,
first-person look
at their u-2 program,
and see just how tough
those planes are to operate.
Oh!
Cool.
What are we waitin' for?
I haven't the slightest idea.
Let's do this.
[ Imitates airplane roaring ]
Man:
It takes off straight up
and looks something like
a jet-propelled four poster.
Narrator:
The history of aviation
is littered
with oxymoronic aerodynamics,
finicky flyers, and design duds.
So is it possible that
one of the most long-lived
and high-valued
U.S. air force vehicles
is also the toughest to fly?
To open this investigation,
there's only one destination.
[ Radio chatter ]
[ Plane engine roaring ]
Well, when you've got questions
about the u-2 plane,
they will get answered here.
I'm standing at the home
of the u-2 program.
This is where the planes
are serviced.
This is where the pilots train
before flying to every corner
of the globe to do their jobs.
We should totally be able
to get to the bottom
of this myth here,
and we might even get to fly it.
Narrator: To begin to understand
just how hard it is
to manage this marvel
of aviation engineering...
Well, Adam, Jamie,
this is the infamous
and venerable u-2 Dragon Lady.
Narrator: ...Major Bartholomew,
who has more u-2 flying hours
than any air force pilot
in history,
runs the guys through the specs.
The original design dates
from the mid-'50s,
Bartholomew: Single engine,
high-altitude, long wingspan,
lots of thrust, lots of lift.
We can take a heavy payload
up to a great altitude
and loiter for a long time.
The challenges this aircraft
presents its pilots
are numerous and significant.
But all the fuel
is kept in the wing.
First up,
the plane can't even support
its own massive wingspan
when it's taking off.
Bartholomew:
When the wing develops lift,
the pogo falls away.
Jamie: Next,
recon missions can be lengthy
and are carried out
at very high altitudes
which requires complex
pressure suit technologies
and extreme safety features.
Everything is so thin
and so light
and just strong enough.
And then,
there's the landing.
It has quite a heavy footprint,
because there's just the one
main gear carrying all the load.
Man: 6, 5, 4...
Jamie: The wheels are along
the center line of the fuselage.
So it's like trying to land
a bicycle.
When the airplane does tip over,
these skids protect the wingtip.
Jamie: And we'll see later
when on approach,
the pilot can't even
see the runway.
Man: 3...2...
Jamie: Yes, we got it down
by a pilot in a chase car.
Man: Two hold at 1 inches.
So far, it's looking
pretty good for the myth.
Narrator:
It's an impressive check list
of piloting challenges,
but where next?
Well, we need to get a look
at this baby in action.
To that end, Jamie and I have
been given the go-ahead
to hitch a ride
to the edge of space.
And we will now embark
on a week-long training program.
Yep, it takes a week just to
learn how to be a passenger.
The problem is, there is only
room for one of us.
[ Air hissing ]
Whoa!
[ Laughs ]
Please, please, please,
let it be me!
So the next story
is deadly drones?
Indeed, it is.
If the press
is to be believed,
drones are totally in our future
delivering our packages
and maybe even our pizzas.
But there are those who think
that they are a deadly danger
hiding in plain sight.
That a simple gust of wind
could send a drone into you
and the propellers could...
[ Blows air ]
Slice your throat
and kill you.
That sounds like
it's custom-made for us.
That's exactly
what I was thinking.
Let's get to testing.
Narrator: But testing the myth
with what?
First up,
Adam and Jamie take a tour
of the full-range
of drone technology,
starting with the super size.
Jamie:
Allow me to introduce
our high-tech custom-built
camera platform.
It's got 8 motors
totaling 2,800 watts of power,
it carries a self-stabilized
high-definition 3-pound camera.
[ Loud voice ] Pretty cool, huh?
[ Loud whirring ]
Narrator: And at the other end
of the scale...
This is your basic
consumer-level multi-roter.
It's on the small side,
but it has all the features
that the large ones do --
propellers, motors --
Jamie: [ Laughs ]
Well, as in any new technology,
there can be casualties.
Narrator: But as per the myth,
would one of those causalities
ever be human?
Could a drone really be deadly?
To begin their quest in earnest,
it's back to the shop,
where Adam has
two mid-range models
most likely to be used
in a commercial delivery.
On the left here is
a fly-it-right-out-of-the-box
small model.
Slightly larger is
an intermediate kit-level model,
which comes with all the pieces
you need to fly.
You just have to assemble them.
This one's apparently
ready to fly,
so I'm gonna give it a shot,
see how easy it actually is.
Aah, aah, aah!
Really easy to fly. [ Laughs ]
Narrator: While the damage done
so far is enlightening...
Aah, aah, aah!
A proof of concept is required.
Ew, it dripped juice on me!
Narrator: To find out
if a multi-roter propeller
could ever cause a flesh wound,
Adam and Jamie have
a standard-size blade
spinning at flight speed
on a stick...
And a chicken.
I think today's lesson is gonna
be fairly self-explanatory.
Whenever you're ready, sir.
[ Blade whirring ]
Yeah! There we go!
Yeah!
Check that out.
That right there, my friends,
that's an injury.
But let's face it,
we're not just talking about
an injury,
we're talking about lethality.
Which means we're really talking
about this vein right here,
the jugular, yeah.
I think if we're gonna
continue testing,
we need to make a neck
as a testing platform
that we can run
our multi-roters into.
Narrator:
Coming up on "Mythbusters"...
Can someone get me a band-aid?
Narrator:
Adam's up to his neck
in the gory story
of a deadly drone.
And...
Bail out, bail out, bail out.
Narrator: ...The guys prepare
for the flight of a lifetime.
Adam: Complex and terrifying.
Narrator: Could a drone delivery
ever be deadly?
Aah!
Narrator: Adam and Jamie have
a promising proof of concept.
Yeah! There we go.
Narrator:
Now, to cut a little deeper.
Now if we're going to be testing
whether one of these
can slice through one of these,
we're gonna need one of each.
And these are easy
to buy at the store.
But these -- well, they're
a little harder to come by.
We're gonna have to
make our own.
And to do that,
I'm gonna use a lot of this...
And this guy right here.
And it's going to spurt blood
if it actually gets cut.
[ Whispers ]
It's gonna be awesome.
Narrator:
Yep, Adam's manufacturing
a mortal mannequin that will
react accurately to an impact.
The basic gist
of what I'm gonna be doing
is casting a neck
out of ballistics gelatin.
How tall is this neck?
Who were these men?
With holes in it that I can fill
with "blood" that will be blue
for televisual purposes.
It needs to be really close
to the edge of the skin.
So I'm gonna effectively
mold those veins
using these brass rods in here.
It's sort of like thinking
inside out and backwards.
Narrator: With the negative mold
of the blood vessels in place,
it's time to prepare
the fake flesh.
As Jamie and I have discovered,
this stuff reacts to a bullet
similar to human flesh,
but to get the tenacity
of skin and muscle,
we need to add this fiberglass
filler to the ballistics gel
as we're casting it
into my mold.
Oh, beauty!
Oh, I'm very pleased with how
this is going so far,
based on nothing.
Narrator: Once set,
it's simply a case of easing
the fleshy throat
free of the mold.
Almost, come on!
[ Bleep ] [ Bleep ]
[ Bleep ]
[ Groaning ]
That's it. All right.
Thank you.
Narrator: Then, Adam plums
the system with blue blood...
Nice!
Narrator: ...And tests his
anatomically accurate jugular.
It's at the right depth
behind the flesh.
That is a bleeding neck.
Narrator:...And requires
the same force to slice.
All right, could someone
get me a band-aid?
Allow me to introduce you to...
Yeah, rolls right off
the tongue.
It is basically a rig
for bleeding
when it senses a lethal injury.
Now, I have more than two veins
in this rig,
even though we have only
two in our neck,
because we can test
multiple times
just by turning the neck.
Yeah, it's, like,
that versatile.
So we can test
as much as we want
and watch bursting blue bl--
blue blood,
blue blood fly out of the veins.
I'm gonna stop talking now.
Narrator: But before
Adam's blue blood dummy
is deployed
in the drone firing line...
It's back
to beale air force base
to tackle the myth that the u-2
is the world's toughest plane
to pilot.
[ Roaring ]
Welcome to altitude, physiology,
and full pressure suit
orientation.
Narrator: Adam and Jamie
are both in training
for an in-flight investigation.
One will fly.
One will be on standby.
Pop your helmet off
just like that.
Narrator:
And they're starting
with several not-so-brief
briefings...
You're gonna have
a suit controller like this.
Narrator:
...About the safety equipment...
Man: It acts as a backup
pressurization system.
Narrator:
...And emergency procedures.
We're gonna teach you
how to parachute safely
to the ground.
Narrator:
These are no minute-long
demonstrations
from a flight attendant.
Primarily, it's to prevent
decompression sickness.
Narrator: And a clear indication
of the enormity of the endeavor.
If you lose cabin pressure,
the suit would inflate...
If you are unconscious,
there are inflaters inside...
During this time, your visor
is gonna freeze over.
You will not be able to see...
So if you have to cut yourself
down from something.
Now, we're nowhere near getting
into one of these planes yet,
but already we've got
all this stuff
that we have to know
how to deal with.
The good news is
you have an ejection seat.
The bad news is
you actually have to
pull your own ejection handle
to get out of the aircraft.
Even something like peeing, uh,
it seems like it's kind of
a complicated ordeal.
Push down, lock it to the side,
and you can begin
your slow,
controlled urination.
I don't -- I don't think
that I wanna -- I don't wanna
be pushing or pulling buttons
without really knowing
exactly what they do.
So it's gonna take
a little practice.
So why all of
this complex equipment?
Why is the u-2 program,
the only program besides NASA...
Man: Absolutely unreal.
Adam:
...And the space program
that utilizes
a full pressure suit?
The primary purpose of wearing
this full pressure suit
is to prevent hypoxia.
Adam:
Well, one is, of course,
because it flies higher
than any other normal airplane
into what they call
the space equivalent zone
above 50,000 feet.
But more primarily
is what happens to us
when we go to that height.
Our bodies have evolved
to process oxygen properly
from sea level to 10,000 feet.
Man:
How much is 8 minus 3?
8 minus 3 is 4.
Adam:
When we go above that,
we cease being able to
functionally take in oxygen.
Man: Put up the switches
or you will die.
Put up the switches.
[ Radio chatter, static ]
Therefore, the suit
and the cabin of the plane
have to artificially induce
the conditions
of atmospheric pressure
in order
so that the pilots stay alive.
That is a significant amount
of technology
to solve that one problem.
Just pull down
on the red lanyard...
It potentially could
whack you on the face...
It releases a hook on
the inside of your harness.
Narrator:
After a full day
of intense
information acquisition...
Day 3 dawns
and our raw recruits...
Time to start training.
Narrator:
...Are getting physical.
Wanna see the coolest part?
Ha ha, look at that! Badge.
Narrator: With a crash course
in what to do
if the plane crashes.
That's three weeks
of army airborne
and parachute training
right there.
That's all you do.
Land!
Adam:
This is pretty cool.
We've just gotten
walked through
all of the different
contingencies that could happen
if we have to bail
out of the plane at altitude.
This is very cool.
What happens when the parachute
lands, how to land.
It's easy to land like so.
Gonna break --
something's broken.
Fascinating.
And most specifically...
There we are.
[ Chuckles ]
I just learned how to
actually lower myself
if I end up landing in a tree
and I'm, like,
hanging above the ground.
[ Groans ]
Ah ha, there we go.
And then lowering myself
safely down to the ground.
Lower myself down.
[ Rope whirs ]
Very nice.
All of this is stuff that I hope
I only ever have to try
here in the safety of this room.
Narrator: It's been a long
and exhausting day.
Bail out, bail out, bail out.
Narrator: And the sheer scale
of the task, technology,
and expertise required to fly
at the edge of space,
could not be more apparent.
Two words come to mind
during all this --
complex and terrifying.
Narrator: Three days of
information overload...
The ejection seat we have
was also used in the first
four flights of
the space shuttle Columbia.
Narrator:...And the rigors
of flying the Dragon Lady
are evident.
But is it the hardest plane
to pilot?
To find out, the Mythbusters
are being prepped to fly
to the edge of space.
These are like
my space jammies.
Narrator:
And despite the high spirits...
[ Woman chuckles ]
All right, sir,
can you hear me?
Yep, I kind of
feel like dancing.
Narrator:...The pressure is on,
literally.
All right, bring your...
[ Speaks indistinctly ]
Narrator: Jamie and Adam
have one final stage of training
to be passed as fit to fly.
Oh.
You doing okay?
That's different.
[ Chuckles ]
In fact,
that doesn't feel very good.
[ Air hisses ]
Ow.
Gonna bring you back down.
I could see somebody
feeling like panicking.
It's just, that's a lot
of stuff to process.
Narrator: They each have
a full systems check
in the pressure suit,
followed by a high-altitude
emergency simulation.
Right now Jamie
is getting fitted
into this high-altitude
pressure chamber.
Right and left gloves
are integrated and locked.
It will replicate
the lack of pressures
that he might experience
under different circumstances
in that very suit.
Narrator: The environment
inside the chamber
will simulate
the flight plan of a u-2.
So, Jamie,
what we're gonna do now
is bring the chamber up
to 5,000 feet,
check the ears and sinuses and
make sure they're clearing okay.
Narrator: If the cabin pressure
of the u-2 was to fail...
How you feelin' right now?
I feel fine.
Narrator:...Jamie needs to prove
he can operate the suit
and emergency systems.
So right now we're just doing
a slow ascent up to, uh,
flight level 4-0-0.
Narrator: As they approach
cruising altitude,
there's a startling reminder
of the dangers involved.
Oh, there we go.
Narrator: A breaker of water
at body temperature
begins to boil.
If Jamie's suit were to fail,
that's what the liquids
in his body would do.
All right, let's go ahead
and try to reach that
ejection handle.
Narrator:
With that thought in mind,
and at maximum altitude,
Jamie has a few tasks
to complete.
Down by
your right buttocks there,
that's the scramble handle.
Pull it up towards your chin
just a little bit. That's good.
Narrator: The final being
the suits automated response
to a sudden cabin pressure
failure.
3...2...1...
And go ahead and pull
that helmet hold down.
[ Clicking sound ]
That was something else.
It's, uh, it's kind of scary,
actually.
1...
There's a lot of force,
and when they, uh,
decompressed rapidly,
it's just like, whoa.
You're sort of feeling like
popcorn. [ Chuckles ]
Narrator: While Jamie clearly
didn't enjoy the experience,
he did pass muster.
[ Chuckles ] Oh, awesome.
Narrator:
Cue fanboy savage.
[ Singsongy ] Oh, the gloves!
The coolest thing about this is,
I'm not just wearing a suit.
I'm not even wearing a machine.
Wow!
Oh, man. That's far out.
[ Air hisses ]
Whoo!
I'm wearing the apex
of decades of tens of thousands
of people problem solving how to
survive in hostile conditions,
and I can feel that technology.
Whoa! [ Laughs ]
I can feel how reliable
they've made things
to touch and understand
with your hands.
All of this borne
by hard experience.
Lots of people gave their lives
so that this suit
could protect these pilots.
Are you good to go?
I am good to go.
Honestly, everything about this
kind of astounds me
that people do this
every single day.
Starting climber 5,000 feet
at 5,000 feet coming up.
Adam:
It takes a team of people
to put me
in this suit correctly.
How's your comfort level?
Well, I'm farting up a storm.
But more than that,
once I was under the simulated
depressurization...
Oh, there we go. Wow.
...where the suit would inflate,
it gets incredibly tiring.
Locate the ejection handle
in between your legs.
Oh, there you go, sir,
your fingers around it.
Yeah, there we go. Okay.
Adam: These guys have to be
in incredible shape
because I was just sitting
in a chair being tested.
These guys are actually
potentially flying planes
under these conditions.
3...2...1...
[ Clicking sound ]
[ Air whooshes ]
Go ahead and pull
that green lanyard.
Use the mirror.
Adam: So, our training is done
and we are ready to fly.
Excellent. Welcome.
Welcome, everyone. [ Chuckles ]
Remember, we went
through all of that
just to be passengers
on the u-2.
Now, we gotta do two things --
one, we gotta figure out
which one of us is gonna fly,
me or Jamie.
And two, we gotta let
these professionals figure out
the logistics
of their flight plan.
Just a little bit of waiting.
Narrator: While Adam and Jamie
wait for flight clearance,
the guys decamp
to the perfect location
for wind-protected
precision flying.
Adam: We are testing the myth
that multi-roters
can possibly be lethal.
So, this is our multi-roter.
This is our multi-roter pilot
James Franklin hyneman.
And this is
our potential victim
with veins filled
with blue blood --
clearly a vulcan
who we're going to steer
this thing right into.
You ready to fly?
Sure.
Okay, here we go.
All right.
[ Drone blades whirring ]
For this first test,
we're gonna get our little
copter up about this high.
I wouldn't want this thing
flying at me.
Sounds like a swarm
of angry bees.
And then drive it right
into the neck of our dummy.
And we'll see what happens
at that speed
with those propellers.
Oh! [ Laughs ]
That was a perfect hit!
And it was going
pretty quick.
[ Beep ]
Oh!
It doesn't seem to me
that anything at all
happened to the neck.
Take a look at the high speed
footage of the multi-roter
hitting the neck.
You can see the props bending
right out of the way
even in the face of something
as soft as neck flesh.
Yeah, clearly,
they were designed to do that.
Narrator: Yep,
the fly-it-out-of-the-box
quad-copter didn't make a dent.
But next up, the kid model.
Aha.
That one's much scarier.
Narrator: More likely to be
used for large deliveries,
it's heavier, has more power,
6 roters,
and sturdier propellers.
Let's see what it can do.
Oh!
Oop. That's no good.
Narrator: Uh, take two?
It's going right for me.
Oh! Oh!
Oh!
[ Laughs ]
Sorry about that.
I'd rather not experiment
on each other.
Narrator: The larger model
is proving trickier to handle.
Aw.
Oh.
Narrator: But eventually,
Jamie gets it going
where he wants it.
Yeah, yeah, yeah,
yeah, yeah, yeah!
Oh, nice!
Well, bigger multi-roter,
bigger propellers,
nice fat hit right here
in the vein, nothing.
No penetration.
I have to say that,
aside from being amazing pieces
of technology,
these multi-roters are
genuinely spooky to be around.
One, they sound like
a hive of angry bees.
[ Drone blades whirring ]
Oh!
Two, I am genuinely physically
afraid of them hitting me.
But apparently, that fear
is without any reason,
because we've been smacking them
into our neck
without any injury whatsoever.
So where does that leave us?
Come on.
We're the Mythbusters.
We're gonna sling
our camera platform into it.
This has 8 roters,
weighs 16 pounds,
and the propellers
are not made of plastic
that bends out of the way.
No, they're made
of carbon fiber.
I'm genuinely scared about
what this is gonna do
to this neck.
Scared and hopeful.
Narrator: The myth that one of
these can cause a lethal injury,
is looking suspect.
He's totally fine.
Narrator:
But the team is dumping the two
realistic mid-range models...
And going for broke
with the "Mythbusters" own
custom-made camera carrying
behemoth.
[ Loudly ] I thought the other
two multi-roters were scary.
Narrator: Cue the team's
expert pilot, Duncan,
and this myth's final chance
for gory glory.
I was wrong.
That thing is terrifying.
Jamie: This large multi-roter
is a different beast
than what we've been
handling earlier.
All right,
shall we do this?
You ready?
Ready.
Jamie: It's much bigger
and heavier.
Once it starts to move
into the neck,
it doesn't wanna just
bounce off
because it's so heavy.
So, I think this is gonna
actually do something
to our neck,
something bad.
Yes!
[ Laughs ]
Look at that!
It's bleeding.
That's bad!
[ Laughs ]
Dude!
Adam: Yes!
There you have it, kids.
It's all fun and games
until someone loses an eye,
or a vein.
You put your finger there,
you'll be fine.
I'm not sure.
So what have we proven
after all this mayhem?
I think we've actually proven
two different things.
On one hand,
the smaller multi-roters
you can buy at the store
are pretty darn safe
and they're designed
to be that way.
But this is a new hobby,
and there are lots of people
building larger
and larger multi-roters
to handle bigger
and bigger payloads.
And when those multi-roters
get bigger,
the dangers they present
are absolutely real.
I know we've been looking
at a worst-case scenario,
but I think we've gotta
call this thing plausible.
Do you agree?
I agree, you know,
as a general rule,
I always try not to
put my neck
near large,
heavy, fast-moving objects
with spinning blades on them.
I think that's
a good general rule.
Let's get out of here.
[ Chuckles ]
Man: 4...3...
Let it down a little...
Narrator: Back at beale,
the guys are ready to carry out
the final test
on the mythically-
difficult-to-fly u-2.
But only one of them
gets to go.
Well... [ sighs ] You know,
for crying out loud,
you're -- you're a fanatic
about this stuff.
You collect these things.
Yeah, I do.
And so, I can't
in good conscience deny you
the, uh, the pleasure
of doing something like that.
I really appreciate that, sir.
Thank you very much.
You owe me one.
Oh, I totally owe you one.
[ Chuckles ]
Absolutely.
[ Under breath ] Yeah! Wah!
Narrator:
Jamie the gentleman steps down.
A very happy Adam steps up.
I'm pretty excited.
Can you tell?
Narrator: ...For the defining,
not quite hands-on test.
Now it's go time to figure out
just how hard this plane
will be to fly.
I won't be flying it,
no, no, no.
I'll just be helping
to assess that.
It is an unbelievable day
here in northern California.
There is barely
a cloud in the sky.
It's incredibly clear.
It is a perfect day
for flying.
So, Adam, the engine's
starting to spool up.
Oh, yeah.
Once that's happened
and we have sufficient r.P.M.,
I'll add a little bit
of, uh, jet fuel here.
Jamie:
Okay, here we go, folks.
Adam's gotta be
freaking out about now.
[ Plane engine roaring ]
All right, Adam, at this point
you need to make sure
that the boost lever is aft
and your t-block there
under your left rib cage
is one notch open.
Yes, it is currently
one notch open.
Boost lever's still aft.
[ Radio chatter ]
I tell you one thing,
this plane is such a unique
and problematic thing to fly
that it requires a lot
of people to make sure
it's all perfect
before it takes off.
All right, the pogo crew
has pulled the pin
so the pogos will fall away
as we take off.
[ Radio chatter ]
All the checklists
have been checked.
We are just seconds away
from taking off.
[ Radio chatter ]
All right, here we go,
break release, full power.
[ Roaring ]
Here we go.
We are taking off.
Oh, man.
That is a lot of horsepower.
That's a -- wow!
We're already lifting!
That's crazy!
Whoa!
Wow!
Man, that's steep.
Wow! We are already lifting.
We're banking hard to the right.
This is part of a, uh,
take off that keeps the u-2
above the base.
We're sort of spiraling
straight up.
Holy cow.
That was so fast!
[ Laughs ]
We're turning on a dime
as we spiral up into the air,
climbing very rapidly.
Narrator:
After a tricky takeoff,
and rapid initial ascent...
Oh, my God,
the view is beautiful!
Narrator: Major Bartholomew
and Adam get a chance
to sit back and relax.
Right now we just passed
the top of mount Everest.
Narrator: Until they attain
cruising altitude.
We're transitioning now
from 160-knot climb to a, uh,
.715 mach cruise.
Three-quarters of
the speed of sound.
This is officially the highest
off the ground I have ever been.
We are coming up on
60,000 feet,
12 Miles above
the surface of the earth.
And the sky has gotten
to be a very, very dark blue.
What an unbelievably
beautiful day.
And from this height,
67,500 feet...
[ Inhales deeply ]
The edge of our planet
has a definitive curve to it.
It is, uh,
more three dimensional
than I have ever seen it.
[ Inhales deeply,
exhales slowly ]
There we are.
Ladies and gentlemen,
70,000 feet.
[ Inhales deeply,
exhales slowly ]
At this point,
aside from the six astronauts
on the space station,
we are the two highest humans
off of planet earth.
More than double the height
of a standard
commercial airliner.
Ha, and did I mention
I'm wearing a pressurized
space suit? Yeah.
Strapped to a rocket.
This is not a bad way
to spend your day.
Jamie,
I totally owe you one.
Narrator: The complex,
exhaustive preparations
and taxing takeoff
seem a world away.
Oh, look at that.
Wow. That is San Francisco.
That's my home.
Narrator: But this is exactly
what the u-2 is designed to do,
spend hours up here
looking down,
gathering intelligence.
The view from a commercial
airliner is beautiful.
This one is transcendent.
Narrator: It's the maneuvers
at either end of proceedings
where the pilots earn
the big bucks.
The challenges in landing
this plane are unique.
And Adam is about to get
a real close look.
We'll be back with our landing
after this commercial break.
[ Laughing ]
Hey, space boy,
how you doin' up there?
Adam:
I'm doin' pretty good, Jamie.
The view up here
is absolutely astonishing.
Looking at it
makes you realize that...
You've left the bulk
of the earth's atmosphere.
That's why it's dark.
You're looking down
at this fragile mist
that surrounds our...
Our globe
that allows us to breathe.
What allows me to do so
is the ingenuity
of thousands and thousands
of hardworking men and women
who have sought to
harness the raw materials
that we dig out of the ground
into things as astonishing
as airplanes
and pressure suits.
[ Inhales deeply,
exhales slowly ]
What a privilege.
Oh, man.
That is a lot of horsepower.
Wow, we're already lifting.
That's crazy!
Whoa! Wow!
Oh, my God,
the view is beautiful.
Wow, look at that.
Narrator: There's no doubt
the high-altitude u-2
is a beautiful piece
of aviation technology.
Captain needed apple pie.
Yeah.
Narrator: But the question
yet to be answered is...
Oh, that's delicious.
Narrator: ...Is it the most
difficult to fly and land?
These guys fly these planes
upwards of 12 to 14 hours
at a time. Mmm.
Narrator: Yep, and after
such mammoth flight times...
You must have some butt
shimmying exercises
you do to keep yourself from
going numb during long flights.
I call it
building your ass-callus.
[ Adam laughs ]
Narrator:
...Comes the landing.
All righty,
ready to begin the descent.
Narrator: This is where
the rubber meets the runway.
Gonna start by dropping
the gears.
So you'll feel
a little bit of a clunk.
Narrator: And perhaps
the biggest challenge
facing any pilot anywhere.
Two gear down and locked.
Now I'm gonna bring
the throttle back.
Narrator: The Dragon Lady
lands tail-wheel first
at a speed that practically
stalls the wing.
And with only two sets
of landing gear
in the center of the fuselage,
it's like landing a bicycle.
The pilot has floored
the landing gear
and implemented
several procedures to add drag
so that it's moving slow enough
when we get to the runway,
then we can actually land.
Narrator: That's not all.
There's the ground effect.
The u-2's high-aspect ratio
wings and commensurate uplift
means that on final approach,
it tends to float,
requiring incredible skill
to control.
There's also the issue
of runway visibility.
This is the chase car
and it's being driven by
an actual u-2 pilot.
Because the pilot in the plane
has such limited visibility
that he can't even see
the runway
when he's down close to it.
This pilot is gonna be
talking him down
with foot-by-foot instructions
so that he can respond
appropriately
at the right time.
Bartholomew: And we're on
our threshold speed.
[ Speaking indistinctly ]
And now
this is the fun part.
This is the part where I earn
the big u-2 pilot bonus money.
All right, so we have one guy
rolling in on final ahead of us.
[ Car engine revs ]
Yee-haw.
We are geared down,
flaps full, speed brakes out,
[ speaks indistinctly ]
Lights on,
and spoilers
in the landing position.
Configured
and ready for landing.
[ Radio chatter ]
Look at that.
Man: 15...12...
10...8...
7...6...5...4...3...
Let it down a little at 4.
3, 2, hold it at 1 inches.
Oh... [ chuckles ]
[ Chuckles ]
[ Beeping ]
[ Monitor beeping rapidly ]
Wow.
Man: Very nice.
Welcome back, gentlemen.
He's required by tradition
to say "very nice"
whether it is or not.
Oh, okay.
It's been a lot of fun.
Thanks, Adam.
And there's our big old
reception committee.
All right, throttle off.
Adam:
All right, editors,
if you could give us
a little montage
of some of the astonishing
things we've gotten to do
in the course
of doing "Mythbusters"...
Welcome back.
Adam: I'm thinking, flying
a rocket car across the desert.
Watching the rocket sled
accelerate to the speed of sound
and hit the immovable wall.
[ Explosion ]
That was awesome!
[ Laughter ]
Sliding down
a 200-foot water slide
at 70 feet through the air
into a target.
Aw, yeah!
Man: He was like, come on!
[ Applause ]
Cheers!
This tops all of those
by a factor of two.
That was unbelievable.
Unrepeatable.
Incredible.
I'm out of superlatives.
I have just spent the last
two hours strapped to a rocket,
wearing a space suit,
flying to the edge
of our earth's atmosphere,
and seeing my hometown
from a vantage point...
Wow!
Bartholomew: That's a great view
of the bridge.
It is an incredible view.
...that was completely unique.
So, Adam, how do you figure
we're gonna call this?
Because, I mean,
this is supposed to be
the most difficult
plane to fly,
but we haven't looked
at any other planes.
Okay, but we did learn this,
it is a completely unique
airframe purpose-built
for a completely
unique mission.
It requires a more numerous
flight crew
and a more exhausted set
of protocols
than any other plane
in the military.
And it is the only
airborne endeavor
besides going to space
that requires
the wearing
of the space suit.
This is not a bad way
to spend your day.
I think that places it
in the plausible category.
Okay.
All right.
I think it also places it
in the "ultra cool" category.
Absolutely.
Let's get out of here.
So, Adam, do you know why
she's called "the Dragon Lady"?
No, I don't.
'Cause you don't know whether
she's gonna land like a dragon
or a lady.
[ Laughs ]