[ 收音机嘎吱嘎吱 ]
[ 尖叫声 ]
[ 风扇呼呼旋转 ]
啊!（￣ε(#￣)
我很抱歉
这些东西
飞起来挺棘手的
对啊，我觉得
如果操纵着大一些的飞行器
你可以造成一些
有效伤害
甚至可能把一个人干掉
等等……
[ 仔细想了想 ]
让我们开始节目吧
-- Captions by vitac --
www.Vitac.Com
captions paid for by
Discovery Communications
[ whirring ]
我猜这个故事是关于
无人机的
是的，但实际上这一集中我们有
两个棒棒哒的
关于飞行器的流言
其中一个是关于
这些家伙
但是首先我们
要讲一个精彩的故事
我问你啊
蛟龙夫人对你来说意味着什么
我不想谈这个
哦尅，我们可能想到不同的方面去了
因为蛟龙夫人
其实是灯塔国空军
在50年代对传奇般的高空侦察机
U-2的昵称
[ 收音机嘎吱嘎吱 ]
行吧，流言是关于什么的
嗯，流言表示
U-2侦察机是所有飞机中
最难操纵起降的飞机
[ 广播中传来
坚定的声音 ]
我觉得我们应该近距离看看他
美国空军是绝对不会
让我们
接近这么个玩意儿的
对讲机： C1, 34.8, 34.8.
我一开始也是这么想的
但是奇迹般的是
他们允许了
你和我
亲自
参观他们的U-2项目
去看看这些
飞机操作是有多难
饿啊
酷
那我们还等什么呢
没什么可等的了
让我们干♂吧
[ 模仿飞机引擎咆哮 ]
Man:
它笔♂直得升起来了
看起来像喷气推进的四柱架子床
Narrator:
航空的历史
被逆向空气动力学
挑剔的飞行员和糟糕的设计再次推动
所以这在世时间最长的
价值最高的
美国空军飞行工具
同时也是最难操纵的？
为开展这个调查
我们该去只有那个地方
[ Radio chatter ]
[ Plane engine roaring ]
我们已经得到那些
有关U-2的疑问
他们将在这里得到一一解答
我现在正站在U-2项目的研发地
这里就是这些飞机被提供服♂务的地方
这里是飞行员训练的地方
在飞到全球各个角落去执行他们的任务之前
我们必须能够
在这里找出流言的真相
我们甚至要登上飞机飞行
Narrator: 为了开始弄懂要完成
这个奇迹般的航空器有多难
亚当，杰米
这就是声名狼藉却又庄严的U-2蛟龙夫人
Narrator:
有着比任何空军飞行员
都久的U-2飞行经历的巴塞洛缪少校
将按照规范训练亚当和杰米
最初设计始于50年代
Bartholomew: 单发引擎,
高空飞行, 超长翼展
超强推力, 超大抬升力
我们可以携带很重的荷载到一个很高的高度
然后续航很久
这架飞行器带给飞行员的挑战
众多且意义重大
但是所有的燃料都装在机翼中
首先，飞机在起飞时并不能支持住
他重量巨大的机翼
Bartholomew:
当机翼即将提升
机翼下方的辅助轮将脱落
Jamie: 然后侦察任务将是漫长的
并且将在一个非常高的高度执行
这需要复杂的增压服科技
和极端情况下的安全保障功能
所有的东西都是这么薄这么轻
却又十分坚固
最关键的是降落
它的降落十分猛烈
以为只有一个主要的起落架承载所有的重
Man: 6, 5, 4...
Jamie: 轮子沿着机身的中心线分布
所以它看起来就像降落一辆自行车
当机身倾向一侧
这些制动垫料将会保护翼梢
Jamie: 我们之后将看到
即使是接近之后
飞行员也无法看到跑道
Man: 3...2...
我们通过另一名驾驶员驾驶追逐车辆来解决这个问题
Man: Two hold at 1 inches.
目前来看，流言的情况不错
Narrator:
这是个令人影响深刻的
对飞行员有着挑战的核对表
但是接下来呢
我们必须亲自看一看这个好东西
为了那个目的，杰米和我已经
被放行
去搭一趟
到宇宙边缘的顺风车
接下来我们将着手于为期一个礼拜的训练项目
是的我们将用一礼拜的时间学习如何成为一名乘客
问题是, 只有一人份的空间供我们中的一个人进去
[ Air hissing ]
WOW!
[ 蛤蛤蛤 ]
求你了x3让我进♂去吧
所以下一个故事是致命无人机？
是，就是，确实是
If the press
is to be believed,
无人机将在未来运送我们的包裹
甚至是我们的披萨
但是有些人认为它们是 致命的危险
潜在的 一目了然
无人机可能将在一阵狂风中袭击你
然后螺旋桨将……咻
切断你的喉咙杀了你
这听起来像
他是为我们定制的
这正是我所想的
让我们去测试吧
Narrator: 但是用什么测试这个流言呢
首先
亚当和杰米全方位的浏览了一下
无人机技术
从巨大的尺寸开始
Jamie:
让我介绍一下
我们的定制摄像平台
它有八个电动机和2800W的动力
它携带着自稳定高解析3磅重相机
[ Loud voice ] 超酷，不是吗?
[ Loud whirring ]
Narrator: 然后在模型的另一边...
这是基础消费级别的四轴飞行器
他麻雀虽小
却五脏俱全
螺旋桨，电机……
Jamie: [ 蛤蛤蛤 ]
任何科技都有它的受害者
Narrator: 但是作为流言的一部分
人类将会成为它的受害者吗
无人机真的可能致命吗
为认真开始他们的探索
需要回到工作室
这里，亚当有两个中规模的模型
最可能用于商业快递
左边的这个是
即时飞出盒子的小模型
大一点的是中级的模型
有着一切你想要飞行的部件
你只要组装起他们
这一个已经准备好飞行了
所以我将试一试这实际上有多容易飞
Aah, aah, aah!
非常容易飞行
当前造成的损伤是非常启蒙性的
Aah, aah, aah!
观念的证据是很需要的
恶，他滴下妹汁在我身上
Narrator: 为了搞明白一个普通螺旋桨
也能造成一条新鲜的伤口
亚当和杰米将一条标准尺寸的叶片
装在棍子上以飞行时的速度旋转
然后一只鸡
今天的教训是肯定是不解自明的
随时待命，Sir
[ Blade whirring ]
液~要来咯
液~
快看看
看就在那里，我的朋友，那里有一个伤口
让我们来面对一下
我们不仅仅在讨论伤口
我们在讨论毁灭性的伤害
这意味着我们确实在讨论这条静脉
这条颈静脉
我觉得如果我们继续试验
我们需要制作一个脖子当做试验平台
我们能够伸进我们的螺旋桨
Narrator:
接下来，在流言终结者
谁能给我搞一条邦迪®创可贴
Narrator:
亚当正将脖子伸向
致命无人机的血腥故事
还有……
跳伞！跳伞！跳伞！
Narrator: ...大家正在准备有生之年的飞行
Adam: 又复杂又吓人
Narrator: 无人机运输会致命吗？
Aah!
Narrator: Adam and Jamie已经准备好了证明
液~来吧
Narrator:
现在，切深一点
既然我们要证明其中一个
可以切进另外一个，我们需要各一个
这是很容易在商店买到的
但是这些就不是那么容易搞定了
我们要自己制作一个
为了做到这个，我要用很多很多的这个
和这个东西
如果他被切断，将喷出血
这将会很精彩
Narrator:
液噗，亚当制造
a mortal mannequin that will
react accurately to an impact.
我将要做的基本要点就是
是铸造一个脖子
用弹道明胶.
这脖子多高，这些人是谁
因为有管子在里面所以我可以灌入蓝色的血液
为了视觉体验
这需要很靠近表皮
所以我将有效地铸造这些静脉
运用这些黄铜棒材
有点像想内想外
Narrator: 随着模具和血管的就位
是时候来制作假肉了
杰米和我发现，这东西和子弹发生的反应
很像人体和子弹所发生的反应
但为了得到皮肤和肌肉的韧性
我们需要把这个玻璃纤维填料添加到弹道凝胶里
当我们在铸造模具时
Oh, 真漂亮!
Oh，到目前为止，我对这一切表示很高兴
不基于任何事情
Narrator: 设置好了以后，就是一段短暂的缓解
新鲜的喉咙从模具中取出
就要出♂来了！
[ Bleep ] [ Bleep ]
[ Bleep ]
[ Groaning ]
好了就是这样，谢谢
Narrator: 然后亚当将蓝色的血加入到系统中
Nice!
Narrator: .然后测试他那在解剖学上完全正确的静脉模型
他就在皮下正确的深度
That is a bleeding neck.
以及需要正确大小的力来切割
好了，谁能给我个邦迪创可贴
让我给你介绍一下
已经介绍的很顺口了
这基本上就是个用来流血的装置
当是致死的伤口
这套系统现在有不止两条静脉
即使我们喉咙只有两条
这样我们就可以测试好几次
只要通过旋转脖子
液，就像是多功能的工具
我们想测试几次就测试几次
还能看蓝色的血液喷出
蓝色的血液从静脉喷出，我要闭嘴了
Narrator: 但是在亚当的蓝血假人之前
is deployed
in the drone firing line...
It's back
to beale air force base
to tackle the myth that the u-2
is the world's toughest plane
to pilot.
[ Roaring ]
Welcome to altitude, physiology,
and full pressure suit
orientation.
Narrator: Adam and Jamie
are both in training
for an in-flight investigation.
One will fly.
One will be on standby.
Pop your helmet off
just like that.
Narrator:
And they're starting
with several not-so-brief
briefings...
You're gonna have
a suit controller like this.
Narrator:
...About the safety equipment...
Man: It acts as a backup
pressurization system.
Narrator:
...And emergency procedures.
We're gonna teach you
how to parachute safely
to the ground.
Narrator:
These are no minute-long
demonstrations
from a flight attendant.
Primarily, it's to prevent
decompression sickness.
Narrator: And a clear indication
of the enormity of the endeavor.
If you lose cabin pressure,
the suit would inflate...
If you are unconscious,
there are inflaters inside...
During this time, your visor
is gonna freeze over.
You will not be able to see...
So if you have to cut yourself
down from something.
Now, we're nowhere near getting
into one of these planes yet,
but already we've got
all this stuff
that we have to know
how to deal with.
The good news is
you have an ejection seat.
The bad news is
you actually have to
pull your own ejection handle
to get out of the aircraft.
Even something like peeing, uh,
it seems like it's kind of
a complicated ordeal.
Push down, lock it to the side,
and you can begin
your slow,
controlled urination.
I don't -- I don't think
that I wanna -- I don't wanna
be pushing or pulling buttons
without really knowing
exactly what they do.
So it's gonna take
a little practice.
So why all of
this complex equipment?
Why is the u-2 program,
the only program besides NASA...
Man: Absolutely unreal.
Adam:
...And the space program
that utilizes
a full pressure suit?
The primary purpose of wearing
this full pressure suit
is to prevent hypoxia.
Adam:
Well, one is, of course,
because it flies higher
than any other normal airplane
into what they call
the space equivalent zone
above 50,000 feet.
But more primarily
is what happens to us
when we go to that height.
Our bodies have evolved
to process oxygen properly
from sea level to 10,000 feet.
Man:
How much is 8 minus 3?
8 minus 3 is 4.
Adam:
When we go above that,
we cease being able to
functionally take in oxygen.
Man: Put up the switches
or you will die.
Put up the switches.
[ Radio chatter, static ]
Therefore, the suit
and the cabin of the plane
have to artificially induce
the conditions
of atmospheric pressure
in order
so that the pilots stay alive.
That is a significant amount
of technology
to solve that one problem.
Just pull down
on the red lanyard...
It potentially could
whack you on the face...
It releases a hook on
the inside of your harness.
Narrator:
After a full day
of intense
information acquisition...
Day 3 dawns
and our raw recruits...
Time to start training.
Narrator:
...Are getting physical.
Wanna see the coolest part?
Ha ha, look at that! Badge.
Narrator: With a crash course
in what to do
if the plane crashes.
That's three weeks
of army airborne
and parachute training
right there.
That's all you do.
Land!
Adam:
This is pretty cool.
We've just gotten
walked through
all of the different
contingencies that could happen
if we have to bail
out of the plane at altitude.
This is very cool.
What happens when the parachute
lands, how to land.
It's easy to land like so.
Gonna break --
something's broken.
Fascinating.
And most specifically...
There we are.
[ Chuckles ]
I just learned how to
actually lower myself
if I end up landing in a tree
and I'm, like,
hanging above the ground.
[ Groans ]
Ah ha, there we go.
And then lowering myself
safely down to the ground.
Lower myself down.
[ Rope whirs ]
Very nice.
All of this is stuff that I hope
I only ever have to try
here in the safety of this room.
Narrator: It's been a long
and exhausting day.
Bail out, bail out, bail out.
Narrator: And the sheer scale
of the task, technology,
and expertise required to fly
at the edge of space,
could not be more apparent.
Two words come to mind
during all this --
complex and terrifying.
Narrator: Three days of
information overload...
The ejection seat we have
was also used in the first
four flights of
the space shuttle Columbia.
Narrator:...And the rigors
of flying the Dragon Lady
are evident.
But is it the hardest plane
to pilot?
To find out, the Mythbusters
are being prepped to fly
to the edge of space.
These are like
my space jammies.
Narrator:
And despite the high spirits...
[ Woman chuckles ]
All right, sir,
can you hear me?
Yep, I kind of
feel like dancing.
Narrator:...The pressure is on,
literally.
All right, bring your...
[ Speaks indistinctly ]
Narrator: Jamie and Adam
have one final stage of training
to be passed as fit to fly.
Oh.
You doing okay?
That's different.
[ Chuckles ]
In fact,
that doesn't feel very good.
[ Air hisses ]
Ow.
Gonna bring you back down.
I could see somebody
feeling like panicking.
It's just, that's a lot
of stuff to process.
Narrator: They each have
a full systems check
in the pressure suit,
followed by a high-altitude
emergency simulation.
Right now Jamie
is getting fitted
into this high-altitude
pressure chamber.
Right and left gloves
are integrated and locked.
It will replicate
the lack of pressures
that he might experience
under different circumstances
in that very suit.
Narrator: The environment
inside the chamber
will simulate
the flight plan of a u-2.
So, Jamie,
what we're gonna do now
is bring the chamber up
to 5,000 feet,
check the ears and sinuses and
make sure they're clearing okay.
Narrator: If the cabin pressure
of the u-2 was to fail...
How you feelin' right now?
I feel fine.
Narrator:...Jamie needs to prove
he can operate the suit
and emergency systems.
So right now we're just doing
a slow ascent up to, uh,
flight level 4-0-0.
Narrator: As they approach
cruising altitude,
there's a startling reminder
of the dangers involved.
Oh, there we go.
Narrator: A breaker of water
at body temperature
begins to boil.
If Jamie's suit were to fail,
that's what the liquids
in his body would do.
All right, let's go ahead
and try to reach that
ejection handle.
Narrator:
With that thought in mind,
and at maximum altitude,
Jamie has a few tasks
to complete.
Down by
your right buttocks there,
that's the scramble handle.
Pull it up towards your chin
just a little bit. That's good.
Narrator: The final being
the suits automated response
to a sudden cabin pressure
failure.
3...2...1...
And go ahead and pull
that helmet hold down.
[ Clicking sound ]
That was something else.
It's, uh, it's kind of scary,
actually.
1...
There's a lot of force,
and when they, uh,
decompressed rapidly,
it's just like, whoa.
You're sort of feeling like
popcorn. [ Chuckles ]
Narrator: While Jamie clearly
didn't enjoy the experience,
he did pass muster.
[ Chuckles ] Oh, awesome.
Narrator:
Cue fanboy savage.
[ Singsongy ] Oh, the gloves!
The coolest thing about this is,
I'm not just wearing a suit.
I'm not even wearing a machine.
Wow!
Oh, man. That's far out.
[ Air hisses ]
Whoo!
I'm wearing the apex
of decades of tens of thousands
of people problem solving how to
survive in hostile conditions,
and I can feel that technology.
Whoa! [ Laughs ]
I can feel how reliable
they've made things
to touch and understand
with your hands.
All of this borne
by hard experience.
Lots of people gave their lives
so that this suit
could protect these pilots.
Are you good to go?
I am good to go.
Honestly, everything about this
kind of astounds me
that people do this
every single day.
Starting climber 5,000 feet
at 5,000 feet coming up.
Adam:
It takes a team of people
to put me
in this suit correctly.
How's your comfort level?
Well, I'm farting up a storm.
But more than that,
once I was under the simulated
depressurization...
Oh, there we go. Wow.
...where the suit would inflate,
it gets incredibly tiring.
Locate the ejection handle
in between your legs.
Oh, there you go, sir,
your fingers around it.
Yeah, there we go. Okay.
Adam: These guys have to be
in incredible shape
because I was just sitting
in a chair being tested.
These guys are actually
potentially flying planes
under these conditions.
3...2...1...
[ Clicking sound ]
[ Air whooshes ]
Go ahead and pull
that green lanyard.
Use the mirror.
Adam: So, our training is done
and we are ready to fly.
Excellent. Welcome.
Welcome, everyone. [ Chuckles ]
Remember, we went
through all of that
just to be passengers
on the u-2.
Now, we gotta do two things --
one, we gotta figure out
which one of us is gonna fly,
me or Jamie.
And two, we gotta let
these professionals figure out
the logistics
of their flight plan.
Just a little bit of waiting.
Narrator: While Adam and Jamie
wait for flight clearance,
the guys decamp
to the perfect location
for wind-protected
precision flying.
Adam: We are testing the myth
that multi-roters
can possibly be lethal.
So, this is our multi-roter.
This is our multi-roter pilot
James Franklin hyneman.
And this is
our potential victim
with veins filled
with blue blood --
clearly a vulcan
who we're going to steer
this thing right into.
You ready to fly?
Sure.
Okay, here we go.
All right.
[ Drone blades whirring ]
For this first test,
we're gonna get our little
copter up about this high.
I wouldn't want this thing
flying at me.
Sounds like a swarm
of angry bees.
And then drive it right
into the neck of our dummy.
And we'll see what happens
at that speed
with those propellers.
Oh! [ Laughs ]
That was a perfect hit!
And it was going
pretty quick.
[ Beep ]
Oh!
It doesn't seem to me
that anything at all
happened to the neck.
Take a look at the high speed
footage of the multi-roter
hitting the neck.
You can see the props bending
right out of the way
even in the face of something
as soft as neck flesh.
Yeah, clearly,
they were designed to do that.
Narrator: Yep,
the fly-it-out-of-the-box
quad-copter didn't make a dent.
But next up, the kid model.
Aha.
That one's much scarier.
Narrator: More likely to be
used for large deliveries,
it's heavier, has more power,
6 roters,
and sturdier propellers.
Let's see what it can do.
Oh!
Oop. That's no good.
Narrator: Uh, take two?
It's going right for me.
Oh! Oh!
Oh!
[ Laughs ]
Sorry about that.
I'd rather not experiment
on each other.
Narrator: The larger model
is proving trickier to handle.
Aw.
Oh.
Narrator: But eventually,
Jamie gets it going
where he wants it.
Yeah, yeah, yeah,
yeah, yeah, yeah!
Oh, nice!
Well, bigger multi-roter,
bigger propellers,
nice fat hit right here
in the vein, nothing.
No penetration.
I have to say that,
aside from being amazing pieces
of technology,
these multi-roters are
genuinely spooky to be around.
One, they sound like
a hive of angry bees.
[ Drone blades whirring ]
Oh!
Two, I am genuinely physically
afraid of them hitting me.
But apparently, that fear
is without any reason,
because we've been smacking them
into our neck
without any injury whatsoever.
So where does that leave us?
Come on.
We're the Mythbusters.
We're gonna sling
our camera platform into it.
This has 8 roters,
weighs 16 pounds,
and the propellers
are not made of plastic
that bends out of the way.
No, they're made
of carbon fiber.
I'm genuinely scared about
what this is gonna do
to this neck.
Scared and hopeful.
Narrator: The myth that one of
these can cause a lethal injury,
is looking suspect.
He's totally fine.
Narrator:
But the team is dumping the two
realistic mid-range models...
And going for broke
with the "Mythbusters" own
custom-made camera carrying
behemoth.
[ Loudly ] I thought the other
two multi-roters were scary.
Narrator: Cue the team's
expert pilot, Duncan,
and this myth's final chance
for gory glory.
I was wrong.
That thing is terrifying.
Jamie: This large multi-roter
is a different beast
than what we've been
handling earlier.
All right,
shall we do this?
You ready?
Ready.
Jamie: It's much bigger
and heavier.
Once it starts to move
into the neck,
it doesn't wanna just
bounce off
because it's so heavy.
So, I think this is gonna
actually do something
to our neck,
something bad.
Yes!
[ Laughs ]
Look at that!
It's bleeding.
That's bad!
[ Laughs ]
Dude!
Adam: Yes!
There you have it, kids.
It's all fun and games
until someone loses an eye,
or a vein.
You put your finger there,
you'll be fine.
I'm not sure.
So what have we proven
after all this mayhem?
I think we've actually proven
two different things.
On one hand,
the smaller multi-roters
you can buy at the store
are pretty darn safe
and they're designed
to be that way.
But this is a new hobby,
and there are lots of people
building larger
and larger multi-roters
to handle bigger
and bigger payloads.
And when those multi-roters
get bigger,
the dangers they present
are absolutely real.
I know we've been looking
at a worst-case scenario,
but I think we've gotta
call this thing plausible.
Do you agree?
I agree, you know,
as a general rule,
I always try not to
put my neck
near large,
heavy, fast-moving objects
with spinning blades on them.
I think that's
a good general rule.
Let's get out of here.
[ Chuckles ]
Man: 4...3...
Let it down a little...
Narrator: Back at beale,
the guys are ready to carry out
the final test
on the mythically-
difficult-to-fly u-2.
But only one of them
gets to go.
Well... [ sighs ] You know,
for crying out loud,
you're -- you're a fanatic
about this stuff.
You collect these things.
Yeah, I do.
And so, I can't
in good conscience deny you
the, uh, the pleasure
of doing something like that.
I really appreciate that, sir.
Thank you very much.
You owe me one.
Oh, I totally owe you one.
[ Chuckles ]
Absolutely.
[ Under breath ] Yeah! Wah!
Narrator:
Jamie the gentleman steps down.
A very happy Adam steps up.
I'm pretty excited.
Can you tell?
Narrator: ...For the defining,
not quite hands-on test.
Now it's go time to figure out
just how hard this plane
will be to fly.
I won't be flying it,
no, no, no.
I'll just be helping
to assess that.
It is an unbelievable day
here in northern California.
There is barely
a cloud in the sky.
It's incredibly clear.
It is a perfect day
for flying.
So, Adam, the engine's
starting to spool up.
Oh, yeah.
Once that's happened
and we have sufficient r.P.M.,
I'll add a little bit
of, uh, jet fuel here.
Jamie:
Okay, here we go, folks.
Adam's gotta be
freaking out about now.
[ Plane engine roaring ]
All right, Adam, at this point
you need to make sure
that the boost lever is aft
and your t-block there
under your left rib cage
is one notch open.
Yes, it is currently
one notch open.
Boost lever's still aft.
[ Radio chatter ]
I tell you one thing,
this plane is such a unique
and problematic thing to fly
that it requires a lot
of people to make sure
it's all perfect
before it takes off.
All right, the pogo crew
has pulled the pin
so the pogos will fall away
as we take off.
[ Radio chatter ]
All the checklists
have been checked.
We are just seconds away
from taking off.
[ Radio chatter ]
All right, here we go,
break release, full power.
[ Roaring ]
Here we go.
We are taking off.
Oh, man.
That is a lot of horsepower.
That's a -- wow!
We're already lifting!
That's crazy!
Whoa!
Wow!
Man, that's steep.
Wow! We are already lifting.
We're banking hard to the right.
This is part of a, uh,
take off that keeps the u-2
above the base.
We're sort of spiraling
straight up.
Holy cow.
That was so fast!
[ Laughs ]
We're turning on a dime
as we spiral up into the air,
climbing very rapidly.
Narrator:
After a tricky takeoff,
and rapid initial ascent...
Oh, my God,
the view is beautiful!
Narrator: Major Bartholomew
and Adam get a chance
to sit back and relax.
Right now we just passed
the top of mount Everest.
Narrator: Until they attain
cruising altitude.
We're transitioning now
from 160-knot climb to a, uh,
.715 mach cruise.
Three-quarters of
the speed of sound.
This is officially the highest
off the ground I have ever been.
We are coming up on
60,000 feet,
12 Miles above
the surface of the earth.
And the sky has gotten
to be a very, very dark blue.
What an unbelievably
beautiful day.
And from this height,
67,500 feet...
[ Inhales deeply ]
The edge of our planet
has a definitive curve to it.
It is, uh,
more three dimensional
than I have ever seen it.
[ Inhales deeply,
exhales slowly ]
There we are.
Ladies and gentlemen,
70,000 feet.
[ Inhales deeply,
exhales slowly ]
At this point,
aside from the six astronauts
on the space station,
we are the two highest humans
off of planet earth.
More than double the height
of a standard
commercial airliner.
Ha, and did I mention
I'm wearing a pressurized
space suit? Yeah.
Strapped to a rocket.
This is not a bad way
to spend your day.
Jamie,
I totally owe you one.
Narrator: The complex,
exhaustive preparations
and taxing takeoff
seem a world away.
Oh, look at that.
Wow. That is San Francisco.
That's my home.
Narrator: But this is exactly
what the u-2 is designed to do,
spend hours up here
looking down,
gathering intelligence.
The view from a commercial
airliner is beautiful.
This one is transcendent.
Narrator: It's the maneuvers
at either end of proceedings
where the pilots earn
the big bucks.
The challenges in landing
this plane are unique.
And Adam is about to get
a real close look.
We'll be back with our landing
after this commercial break.
[ Laughing ]
Hey, space boy,
how you doin' up there?
Adam:
I'm doin' pretty good, Jamie.
The view up here
is absolutely astonishing.
Looking at it
makes you realize that...
You've left the bulk
of the earth's atmosphere.
That's why it's dark.
You're looking down
at this fragile mist
that surrounds our...
Our globe
that allows us to breathe.
What allows me to do so
is the ingenuity
of thousands and thousands
of hardworking men and women
who have sought to
harness the raw materials
that we dig out of the ground
into things as astonishing
as airplanes
and pressure suits.
[ Inhales deeply,
exhales slowly ]
What a privilege.
Oh, man.
That is a lot of horsepower.
Wow, we're already lifting.
That's crazy!
Whoa! Wow!
Oh, my God,
the view is beautiful.
Wow, look at that.
Narrator: There's no doubt
the high-altitude u-2
is a beautiful piece
of aviation technology.
Captain needed apple pie.
Yeah.
Narrator: But the question
yet to be answered is...
Oh, that's delicious.
Narrator: ...Is it the most
difficult to fly and land?
These guys fly these planes
upwards of 12 to 14 hours
at a time. Mmm.
Narrator: Yep, and after
such mammoth flight times...
You must have some butt
shimmying exercises
you do to keep yourself from
going numb during long flights.
I call it
building your ass-callus.
[ Adam laughs ]
Narrator:
...Comes the landing.
All righty,
ready to begin the descent.
Narrator: This is where
the rubber meets the runway.
Gonna start by dropping
the gears.
So you'll feel
a little bit of a clunk.
Narrator: And perhaps
the biggest challenge
facing any pilot anywhere.
Two gear down and locked.
Now I'm gonna bring
the throttle back.
Narrator: The Dragon Lady
lands tail-wheel first
at a speed that practically
stalls the wing.
And with only two sets
of landing gear
in the center of the fuselage,
it's like landing a bicycle.
The pilot has floored
the landing gear
and implemented
several procedures to add drag
so that it's moving slow enough
when we get to the runway,
then we can actually land.
Narrator: That's not all.
There's the ground effect.
The u-2's high-aspect ratio
wings and commensurate uplift
means that on final approach,
it tends to float,
requiring incredible skill
to control.
There's also the issue
of runway visibility.
This is the chase car
and it's being driven by
an actual u-2 pilot.
Because the pilot in the plane
has such limited visibility
that he can't even see
the runway
when he's down close to it.
This pilot is gonna be
talking him down
with foot-by-foot instructions
so that he can respond
appropriately
at the right time.
Bartholomew: And we're on
our threshold speed.
[ Speaking indistinctly ]
And now
this is the fun part.
This is the part where I earn
the big u-2 pilot bonus money.
All right, so we have one guy
rolling in on final ahead of us.
[ Car engine revs ]
Yee-haw.
We are geared down,
flaps full, speed brakes out,
[ speaks indistinctly ]
Lights on,
and spoilers
in the landing position.
Configured
and ready for landing.
[ Radio chatter ]
Look at that.
Man: 15...12...
10...8...
7...6...5...4...3...
Let it down a little at 4.
3, 2, hold it at 1 inches.
Oh... [ chuckles ]
[ Chuckles ]
[ Beeping ]
[ Monitor beeping rapidly ]
Wow.
Man: Very nice.
Welcome back, gentlemen.
He's required by tradition
to say "very nice"
whether it is or not.
Oh, okay.
It's been a lot of fun.
Thanks, Adam.
And there's our big old
reception committee.
All right, throttle off.
Adam:
All right, editors,
if you could give us
a little montage
of some of the astonishing
things we've gotten to do
in the course
of doing "Mythbusters"...
Welcome back.
Adam: I'm thinking, flying
a rocket car across the desert.
Watching the rocket sled
accelerate to the speed of sound
and hit the immovable wall.
[ Explosion ]
That was awesome!
[ Laughter ]
Sliding down
a 200-foot water slide
at 70 feet through the air
into a target.
Aw, yeah!
Man: He was like, come on!
[ Applause ]
Cheers!
This tops all of those
by a factor of two.
That was unbelievable.
Unrepeatable.
Incredible.
I'm out of superlatives.
I have just spent the last
two hours strapped to a rocket,
wearing a space suit,
flying to the edge
of our earth's atmosphere,
and seeing my hometown
from a vantage point...
Wow!
Bartholomew: That's a great view
of the bridge.
It is an incredible view.
...that was completely unique.
So, Adam, how do you figure
we're gonna call this?
Because, I mean,
this is supposed to be
the most difficult
plane to fly,
but we haven't looked
at any other planes.
Okay, but we did learn this,
it is a completely unique
airframe purpose-built
for a completely
unique mission.
It requires a more numerous
flight crew
and a more exhausted set
of protocols
than any other plane
in the military.
And it is the only
airborne endeavor
besides going to space
that requires
the wearing
of the space suit.
This is not a bad way
to spend your day.
I think that places it
in the plausible category.
Okay.
All right.
I think it also places it
in the "ultra cool" category.
Absolutely.
Let's get out of here.
So, Adam, do you know why
she's called "the Dragon Lady"?
No, I don't.
'Cause you don't know whether
she's gonna land like a dragon
or a lady.
[ Laughs ]